<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A very profitable treatise made by M. Ihon Caluyne, declarynge what great profit might come to al christendome, yf there were a regester made of all sainctes bodies and other reliques, which are aswell in Italy, as in Fraunce, Dutchland, Spaine, and other kingdomes and countreys. Translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Steuen Wythers. 1561. Set furth and authorised according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
            <title>Traité des reliques. English.</title>
            <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1561</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17729</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4467</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112756</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848001</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848001</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13073</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17729)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13073)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 491:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A very profitable treatise made by M. Ihon Caluyne, declarynge what great profit might come to al christendome, yf there were a regester made of all sainctes bodies and other reliques, which are aswell in Italy, as in Fraunce, Dutchland, Spaine, and other kingdomes and countreys. Translated out of Frenche into Englishe by Steuen Wythers. 1561. Set furth and authorised according to the Queenes Maiesties iniunctions.</title>
                  <title>Traité des reliques. English.</title>
                  <author>Calvin, Jean, 1509-1564.</author>
                  <author>Wythers, Stephen.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[128] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Rouland Hall, dwellyng in Goldyng lane at the sygne of the thre arrowes,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Prynted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1561]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of Jean Calvin's "Advertissement tres utile du grand proffit qui reviendroit à la Chrestienté, s'il se faisoit invẽtoire de tous les corps sainctz, &amp; reliques", commonly known as Traité des reliques.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A treatise of reliques.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Relics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Reliquaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">A VE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry profitable trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>TISE, MADE BY M. IHON</hi> Caluyne, declarynge what great profit might come to al chriſten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, yf there were a regeſter made of all Sainctes bodies and other reliques, which are aſwell in Italy, as in Fraunce, Dutchland, Spaine, and other kingdomes and countreys.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="roman">Tranſlated out of Frenche into Engliſh by Steuen Wythers.</hi> 1561.</p>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>¶Set furth and authoriſed according to the Queenes Maieſties Iniunctions.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>¶Prynted at London by Rouland Hall, dwellyng in Goldyng lane at the ſygne of the thre arrowes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div rend="blackletterType" type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:2"/>
            <head>A very neceſſary TREATISE OF THE BO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyes and reliques of Sain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctes and martyrs.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Ainct Auguſtine in the booke which he entituled: Of the labour of Monkes, complayning of cer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>taine trifle bearers, who already in hys time did exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe a moſt vilainous &amp; filthy kynd of cariyng hyther, and thether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques of martyrs, addeth, yea yf they be reliques of marters. By the which word he ſignifieth: that euen then the abuſe and deceyt herein was committed in making the poore ſimple people to beleue that bones gathered here &amp; there, were the bones of ſaynctes.</p>
            <p>But ſeing the originall of this ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uſe is of ſuch antiquitie, it is not to be doubted, but that it hath ben in the meane while by ſo long con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinuaunce of time greatly multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied: eſpecially ſeyng the worlde
<pb facs="tcp:13073:3"/> ſince that tyme, is merueylouſlye corrupted, and hath declined from worſe to worſe, euen vntill it be come to the extremitie in the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch we ſee it.</p>
            <p>Nowe the firſt vice, as it were the roote of this euill, hath bene this, that in ſtede of ſeking Chriſt in his worde &amp; in his ſacraments, and his ſpirituall graces, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world accordyng to the olde wont therof hath bene occupied in the renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his garmentes, ſhyrtes and other lyke cloutes: and in ſo doing hath left the principall to folowe the acceſſary. In like maner hath it done concernyng the apoſtles, martyrs, and other ſainctes.</p>
            <p>For in ſteade of imitating their li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues, to folowe their examples it hath ben geuen wholly to contem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plate and reſerue as a treaſure, their bones, ſhyrtes, girdles, cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes and other lyke baggage and trifles. I knowe righte well that thys hath a certaine kinde and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of good deuotion and zeale,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:3"/> whyleſt ſome alledge that they kepe the reliques of Ieſus Chriſt for the honor they beare to him, &amp; for the intent to haue a better me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>morie of him: &amp; ſo likewiſe of the ſaincts: but we muſt conſider that which ſainct Paule ſayeth, that all ſeruyce of God inuented by mans braine, what ſhew ſo euer it hath of wiſdome is not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding but vanitie and foliſhnes: yf it haue not a better and more ſure grounde, then our ſeming or iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement.</p>
            <p>Moreouer it behoued to waigh the profyte that myghte comme thereof with the danger: and in ſo doing it woulde haue bene founde to haue bene very litle profitable or altogether ſuperfluous &amp; vaine to haue the reliques in ſuch ſorte: and contrariwiſe it is verye harde or altogether impoſſible that ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by men ſhoulde not decline by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle and litle to ydolatry. For man can not kepe himſelf in the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng and handling of them, but
<pb facs="tcp:13073:4"/> he will alſo honor them: and in ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>noring them, there is no meaſure but incontinent life that is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted vnto them the which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perteyneth onely to Ieſus Chriſt. So then to ſpeake briefly as the thing is, the deſire to haue reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques is almoſt neuer without ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pition, and that worſe is, it is the mother of ydolatry, which is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narely connexed and ioyned ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. Euery man doeth confeſſe that the cauſe that moued oure Lord to hyde the body of Moyſes, was for feare leaſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, ſhoulde abuſe it in worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of it. Now it behoueth to vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtande that, that which hath bene done in one ſainct is done in al the reſt, ſeyng that there is one ſelfe ſame reaſon touching all: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we leaue to ſpeake of the ſaynctes here, yet let vs marke what ſainct Paule ſayeth euen of Ieſus Chriſt himſelfe, for he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſteth not to know him any more according to the fleſhe, after his re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſurrection:
<pb facs="tcp:13073:4"/> admoniſhyng by theſe wordes that all that is carnall in Ieſus Chriſt oughte to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſet aſide to the ende to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye and ſet our affection to ſeke and poſſeſſe him according to the ſpirite.</p>
            <p>Now then to pretende that it is a goodly thyng to haue ſome me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall as well of hym as of the ſainctes, for to ſtyrre vp to deuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. What is this els, but a falſe cloke to paint out our foliſhe and vayne deſier, whiche is grounded on no reaſon? And when this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſhoulde ſeme to be ſufficient, yet for ſo much as it dothe mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtlye repugne to that which the holye goſt hath pronunced by the mouth of ſainct Paul, what wold we haue more? Although it be not now nedefull to diſpute longe vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this poynct: to wit, whether it be good or euill to haue reliques for to kepe them only as precious thynges wythout worſhippynge them. For euen as we haue ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:13073:5"/> experience ſheweth that the one is almoſt neuer with out the other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">In the ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the death of Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</hi>
               </note>It is very trew that ſainct Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe ſpeaking of Helene mother to the Emperour Conſtantine, who with great payne and great expences ſoughte the croſſe of our Lorde: ſayeth that ſhe worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped only the lord that had hanged thereon and not the wodde. But it is a very rare thing to haue the hart addicted to any kinde of reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques whatſoeuer they be, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one do not by &amp; by defile &amp; polute him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wyth ſome kynde of ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. I grant that men do not com incontinently or at the firſt to ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt Idolatrie: but by litle and li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle thei com fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one abſuſe to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, euen vntyll they fall to the extremitie. So much there is that the people that name themſelues Chriſtians, are come euen to this poynte that they haue in this caſe committed as great ydolatrye as euer did the heathen. For they haue bowed them ſelues and kne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:13073:5"/> before the reliques, euen as be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore god. They haue lyghted can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles and torches in ſygne of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and honour. They haue put their truſt in them: they haue had theyr refuge to them, as though the vertue and grace of God had bene encloſed in them. If ydolatry conſiſt in tranſferryng the honor of God to others, ſhall we denye this to be ydolatry? Neither muſt we excuſe the matter in ſayinge, that it hath ben a diſordinat zeale of certaine rude and foliſhe people or of ſimple women: For it hath bene a general diſorder, approued of them which had the guydynge and gouernement of the churche. And likewiſe thei haue placed the bones of the dead, and all other re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liques vpon the high aulter, and on higheſt and moſt euident pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the end to make them with more authoritie honoured.</p>
            <p>Beholde then howe the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this foliſhe curioſitie that men haue had in tymes paſte, to
<pb facs="tcp:13073:6"/> make a treaſure of Reliques, is come euen to thys moſt manifeſt abhomination, that not only men haue turned the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues altogether fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, for to occupy their minds on vayne and corruptible things, but alſo by a moſt execrable ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, haue worſhipped dead and inſenſible creatures in ſteade of the onely liuyng God.</p>
            <p>Now as one euil is neuer alone, but that it draweth another w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it: this miſcheuous wickedneſſe is crept in ſince that men haue recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued for reliques aſwell of Ieſus Chriſt as of the ſainctes, I cannot tell what fylthineſſe and baggage wherein is neither rime nor rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And the worlde hath bene ſo blinded, that what title ſo euer were geuen to euerye trifle that was preſented vnto it, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame was forthwith receyued withoute all iudgement or further inquiſition.</p>
            <p>So that what bones ſo euer of Aſſes or Dogges, that the firſte mocker or deceyuer woulde haue
<pb facs="tcp:13073:6"/> had preferred for bones of martirs men haue made no difficultie to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue them verye deuoutlye. As much hath bene of all the reſt: as it ſhalbe hereafter entreated. For my part I doubt not it hath bene a iuſt puniſhment of god. For ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng the worlde hath gone a mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng after reliques, to abuſe them vnto a moſt peruerſe kinde of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition: it ſtode with good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that god ſhuld permit that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter one lye another ſhould folow.</p>
            <p>On this maner was he wonte to aduenge hym ſelfe of the diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure that hath bene done to his name, when that men did tranſfer his honour to others.</p>
            <p>Wherefore in that there are ſo many falſe and counterfeyte reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques throughout the whole world this procedeth from none other cauſe, but that god hath permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that the world (for ſo much as it did delight in deceyte and lying) ſhoulde be double begyled and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued. It had bene the parte or
<pb facs="tcp:13073:7"/> dutye of chriſtians to haue left the bodies of ſaincts in their graues, for to haue obeyed to this vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſentence. That all men are duſt, and to duſt thei ſhal returne. And not for to lifte them vp in pompe and ſumptuouſnes, for to make as it were a reſurrection be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time. This was not ment but to the contrary againſt the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of god, they haue vnburied the bodies of the faithfull, for to exalt them in glory, whereas they oughte to haue bene in their gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues and reſtyng places, waityng for the latter day. Man hath deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to haue them, and hath put his truſte in them, he hath honored them and hath made all ſignes of reuence to them. And what hath folowed? The Diuil ſeyng men ſo amaſed, was not content to haue deceyued the worlde in one ſort, but hath ſet forth this other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit, to geue titles of reliques of ſainctes to that which was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether prophane. And god by hys
<pb facs="tcp:13073:7"/> vengeance hath taken awaye vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding &amp; iudgement from the vnbeleuers: in ſuch ſort that with out any further inquiſition, they haue accepted al what ſoeuer hath bene preſented vnto them, put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting no difference betwene white and blacke. Now for this preſent I minde not to entreate what ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination it is to abuſe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques aſwell of our Lorde Ieſus as of the ſainctes, in ſuch ſorte as men haue hitherto done, and as is yet done in the moſt part of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtendome, for it woulde require a whole boke to deduce this matter But for aſmuch as it is a thing no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>torious &amp; knowen, that the moſt parte of the reliques that are ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed throughout al places ar falſe and counterfaite, and haue bene ſet forth and preferred by decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, who impude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly haue abuſed the world: I haue thought good to ſpeake ſomwhat therof, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end to giue occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to think thereon, &amp; to take hede therto, for ſomtime we aproue a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g raſhly,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:8"/> For ſo muche as our mindes are occupied in ſuch ſort that we take not leaſure to examine what it is to the ende to giue good and right iudgement: &amp; ſo we fayle for lacke of takyng heede. But when one doeth admoniſhe vs, we beginne to thinke thereon, and are wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous much amaſed, how we haue bene ſo eaſye and lyght to beleue that which was in nothyng pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. Eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo hath it com to paſſe in thys matter, herein for lack of aduertiſement euerye one beyng preoccupied with that which he heareth ſayde: beholde the body of ſuch a ſainct, beholde his ſhowes, behold hys hoſe, ſuffereth himſelf to be perſuaded that it is ſo. But when I ſhal haue euendently ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed the deceyte that is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted therein, who ſo euer hath any ſparke of wiſdome and reaſon wil open hys eyes, and giue him ſelfe to conſider that which neuer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he thought vpon.</p>
            <p>Although I cannot do as I wold
<pb facs="tcp:13073:8"/> in this litle boke. For it ſhould be nedful to haue regeſters fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, for to knowe what reliques are ſayde to be in all places, to the ende to make compariſon of them And then men ſhoulde know that euery Apoſtle ſhoulde haue more then foure bodyes, &amp; euery ſainct at the leaſt two or thre and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhould be of all the reſt.</p>
            <p>To be ſhorte when one ſhoulde haue gathered all on a heape, there is no man that woulde not be aſtoniſhed, ſeyng a mockery ſo foliſh and abſurde, the which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheles hath had power to blind the whole earth.</p>
            <p>I thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for as much as ther is not ſo lytle a cathedrall church that hath not as it wer thouſands of bones and other ſuch litle tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles, what ſhuld it be if one ſhould gather together the whole mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of two or thre thouſande biſhoprickes, of twentye or thyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand abbeys, of more then fourtye thouſande couentes, of ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13073:9"/> many pariſhe churchs &amp; chappels? But yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe &amp; principal ſhuld be to viſet them, &amp; not to name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only, for thei ar not al ſo knowen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei can be named. In this town thei had (as men ſay) in times paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, an arme of S. Anthony y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it was incloſed in a glaſſe they kiſſed and worſhipped: but at ſuch time as it was take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out &amp; ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed forth, it was fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of an Hart: there was alſo on the high aulter hangyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> braine of Sainct Peter as longe as it was incloſed men did not doubte therof. For it had bene blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie not to beleue the ſuperſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. But when as the neſte was pulled out, and that men did bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beholde it, it was founde to be a marble ſtone, I could recite ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thinges by like examples, but theſe ſhall ſuffice to do you to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande what great filthines &amp; ordure ſhoulde be diſcloſed if there were ſome good vniuerſall viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation made of all the reliques
<pb facs="tcp:13073:9"/> of Europa: Yea, and that with wiſedome and prudence to knowe how to diſcerne them.</p>
            <p>For many beholdyng a relique ſhut their eyes through ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the ende, that they ſeing ſhoulde ſee nothyng at all: that is to ſay that they dare not looke in good earneſt to conſider what the thing is. Euen as many that boſt them ſelues to haue ſene S. Glou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des bodye whole, or the bodye of ſome other ſainct: and haue neuer had this boldnes to lifte vp theyr eyes to beholde what the thynge was. But he that ſhould haue the libertie to ſee the ſecreat, and the boldneſſe to vſe it, ſhoulde well know how to ſpeake otherwiſe.</p>
            <p>As much is of the head of Mary Magdeline, which is ſhowed nere the towne of Marſeilles wyth the morſel of paſt, or ware that is fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened vpon her eye. Men do make a treaſure of her, as it were a god deſcended from heauen: but if a tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>al wer made of things men might
<pb facs="tcp:13073:10"/> clearely finde the deceyt and craft. It wer then a thing to be deſired, to haue a certentie of al the trifles that men kepe heare, and there for reliques: or at the leaſt to haue a regeſter of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſhew how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny falſhodes there are? But ſeyng this is not poſſible to be done, I wiſhe to haue onely the Inuento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of ten or twelue townes: as of Paris, Thoulous, Raines, and Poiters: yf I had but onely theſe, (yet neuertheleſſe) men ſhoulde ſee a meruelous great ſwarme, or at the leaſt a confuſed heape. And it is a wiſhe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue many times deſired that I might recouer ſuche an Inuentory: neuertheles for ſo much as y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> would alſo be hard for me to doe, I thought it much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the ende to giue this lytle aduertyſement which foloweth: To the ende to awake them that ſlepe, and to make them thynke what may be ſayd of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber, when that in ſo very a lytle a portion, there is founde ſo much
<pb facs="tcp:13073:10"/> abuſe. I meane, when there ſhall be founde ſo much vntrueth in thoſe Reliques whiche I ſhall name, the which is almoſt not the thouſande parte of that which is ſhewed and ſene: what maye one thynke of the reſidue?</p>
            <p>Moreouer, if it apear that thoſe which were counted and eſtemed for the moſte certayne haue bene fraudulently inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted and counter feyted: what maye men thynke of thoſe that are more doubtfull? And woulde to god that Chriſten Princes would ſomewhat thinke vpon thys. For it were their of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and dutye not to ſuffer theyr pore ſubiects to be ſo deceiued, not onely by falſe doctrine, but viſibly in makynge them beleue (as the Prouerbe ſayeth) that Rammes bladders are lanternes: for they ſhall make accounte before God for their diſſimulyng, yf ſeing and beholdyng the ſame they kepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence: and it ſhall be dearely ſolde them to haue permitted men to
<pb facs="tcp:13073:11"/> mocke God, where as they myght haue remedied the ſame.</p>
            <p>How ſoeuer it be, I truſt that this lytle treatiſe ſhal ſerue al, geuing euery one occaſion to thinke with himſelfe that which the tytle im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteth: that is, yf there were a re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geſter made of all the reliques of the worlde, that men ſhould clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſee how they haue bene decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued and blynded heretofore, and what darkennes and ignoraunce hath bene throughoute the whole earth.</p>
            <p>Let vs begynne then at Ieſus Chriſte, of whome becauſe they coulde not ſaye that they had the naturall body (for concerning hys miraculous body they haue found ſuch meanes to forge it, and that in ſuch number and at all times, as often as ſemed good to them) they haue gathered in ſtede therof thouſands of other trifles, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plye this want. Although yet not withſtanding they haue not to let the bodye of Ieſus Chriſt eſcape with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:13073:11"/> retaynyng ſome lytle gobbet thereof. For beſides the teath and the heare, the Abbey of Charour in the dioſis of Poiters, vanteth it ſelfe to haue the prepuce, that is to ſaye: the foreſkyn that was cut from him in the circumciſion.</p>
            <p>I prai you from whence came this ſkinne vnto them? Sainct Luke the Euangeliſt reciteth very well that our Lord Ieſus was circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed: but that the ſkinne was loc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vp to be reſerued for a relique he maketh no mencion at all: All the auncient hiſtories ſpeake ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer a worde thereof. And for the ſpace of fiue hundred yeres it was neuer ſpoken of in the Chriſtian churche. Where is it then that it was hidden, for to be founde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne ſo ſodenly? Moreouer howe coulde it flye vnto Charour? But for to proue it to be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thyng, they ſay that certain droppes of bloode fell from it. This is their ſaying, which had nede of probation. Wherefore a man maye well ſee,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:12"/> that it is but a plaine mockery or delution. Yet neuertheleſſe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that we ſhoulde graunte them that the ſkynne that was cut from Ieſus Chriſt was kepte and that it might be either there, or els where.</p>
            <p>What ſhould we ſai of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſkinne which is ſhewed at Rome, at Sainct Iohn of Latrans?</p>
            <p>It is moſt certain that there was neuer but one. It coulde not be then at Rome and at Charour both together. So then beholde, a moſt manifeſt faſhold and deceite.</p>
            <p>There remanieth afterwardes the blood, for the which there hath bene great ſtryfe and much diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: For many haue ſayde, that there was found no blood of Ieſus Chriſt, but miraculous bloode, yet neuertheleſſe it is ſhewed natural in more then an hundred places. In one place certaine droppes, as at Rochell in Poitou the whiche Nicodemus (as they ſaye) dyd ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his gloue. In other places
<pb facs="tcp:13073:12"/> violes full, as at Mantone and els where, in other places gobblets ful as at Rome, at ſainct Euſtace. Yea men haue not bene content to haue bloode alone, but they muſt haue mingled it wyth water as it did iſſue out of his ſide when he was pearced on the croſſe. This merchandiſe is to be founde in the church of S. Iohn of Latran at Rome. I leaue the iudgement to euery man what certentie may be had hereof. And namelye whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this be not a manyfeſt lye, to ſay that the blood of Ieſus Chriſt hath bene founde ſeuen or eyghte hundred yeres after his death, for to be ſhewed throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> world: ſeing that in the auncient churche there was neuer made mencion thereof.</p>
            <p>There foloweth after, that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch did touche the body of our lorde Ieſus: or rather al that thei could gather together for to make reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of in memorie of him in ſtede of hys bodye.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:13"/>
            <p>Fyrſt of all the Maunger, in the which he was put at the tyme of his birth, is to be ſhewed at Rome in the church called our Ladye the greater. Alſo in S. Paules church the clothe wherein he was wrap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped: although that there be ſome lytle part of it at S. Sauiours in Spaine. Hys Cradle is alſo at Rome, wyth the ſhyrte that hys mother Mary the Virgyn made hym.</p>
            <p>Item in ſ. Iames church at Rome they doe ſhewe the aulter on the whiche he was ſet in the temple, in the time of his preſentacion: as though there had then bene dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers aulters, as they make in the Papiſtrie as manye as they wyll. So herein they lie without colour or cloke. Beholde what thynges they haue had for the time of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes childhode. It is now not nede full to diſpute muche where it is, that they haue founde all this bag<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gage, ſo longe a tyme ſynce the death of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:13"/>
            <p>For there is none of ſo litle iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that doth not ſee their foly. Throughout the whole hiſtorie of the goſpell, there is not ſo muche as one worde mencioned of theſe thynges. In the tyme of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles it was neuer harde once ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of.</p>
            <p>Aboute fyftye yeares after the death of Chriſt Ieſus, Ieruſalem was beſeiged and deſtroyed. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny auncient doctours haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſenſe that tyme, makyng men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cion of thinges that were in their tyme: namelye of the croſſe and nayles that Helene did finde. But of al theſe ſmal trifles thei ſpeake neuer a worde. Moreouer in the time of Sainct Gregory, it is out of all dout that there was none of all this at Rome, as may be ſeene by his writynges. After whoſe death Rome hath bene diuers ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes taken, pylled, and almoſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together waſted. When all this ſhalbe conſidered, what can one ſaye els, but that all this geare
<pb facs="tcp:13073:14"/> hath bene deuiſed for to abuſe the ſimple people. And in verye deede the maſkers as well Prieſtes as Monkes, do well confeſſe that it is ſo, in callynge them <hi rend="roman">Pias fraudes,</hi> that is to ſay honeſt deceytes, for to moue the people to deuotion.</p>
            <p>There foloweth reliques which appertain to the time that is ſince the childhode of Ieſus Chriſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll his death. Amonges which there is the piller whereon he dyd leane when he diſputed in the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple, with eleuen other lyke pyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers of Salomons temple, I aſke them who did reuele vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that Ieſus did leane vpon a pyller?</p>
            <p>For the Euangeliſt maketh no mencion therof, in rehearſing the hiſtorie of this diſputacion. And it is not lykely to be trew, that thei gaue him place as vnto a preacher ſeyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was not in eſtimacion, nor in authoritie as it doth apear. Moreouer, I demaunde although that he had leaned vpon a piller, yet howe is it that they knowe it
<pb facs="tcp:13073:14"/> to be the ſame? Thyrdlye from whence that they haue had theſe twelue pyllers whiche they ſaye were of the temple of Salomon.</p>
            <p>There foloweth after the cruſes wherein the water was that Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt chaunged into wyne at the bride ale in Cana of Galilee, the which they call Hydries.</p>
            <p>I woulde gladly knowe who was the keper of them ſo longe a time, for to diſtribute theym. For we muſt note this that they were not found before .viii. C. or a thouſand yeres after that this miracle was done. I doe not knowe all places where they are ſhewed. I knowe well that ther are of them at Piſe at Rauene, at Cluny, at Angers, at S. Sauiours in Spaine.</p>
            <p>But without makyng further diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>courſe of the matter, it is very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye, onely by the eye ſyght, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince them of a lye. For ſome of them do contain no more but fiue quartes of wine at the moſt, other ſome leſſe: &amp; the others do contain
<pb facs="tcp:13073:15"/> wel nigh a firken. Let them make theſe floutes agre, if thei can: and then I wyll leaue them their Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dries without makynge any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies with them. But they haue not bene content wyth the veſſels onely except they had ther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the drinke alſo: for at Orleance they ſaye that they haue the wine the which thei name Achitricline. For becauſe the Euangeliſt ſainct Iohn recityng the miracle, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the Architricline, which is to ſay the maiſter of the houſe.</p>
            <p>It hath ſemed to them that it was the proper name of the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grome: and they entertayne the people in thys beaſtlyneſſe.</p>
            <p>For once a yere they make them that wyll brynge them their offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe: licke the ende of a ſponne, telling them that they geue them to drink of the wyne that our lord made in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> banquet. And the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titie neuer diminiſheth (prouided alwaies that thei fil the gobblet).</p>
            <p>I can not tel of what bignes his
<pb facs="tcp:13073:15"/> ſhowes are, which are ſaid to be at Rome in the place named <hi rend="roman">Sancta ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> nor whether they be thoſe that he ware in his childholde, or in his manhode. And when all is ſayd a like worth is the one as the other. For that whiche I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſayde, doth ſufficiently ſhew what impudencye it is, to brynge forth nowe the Showes of Chriſt whyche the Apoſtles them ſelues had not in their time.</p>
            <p>Let vs come to that which doth appertayne to the laſte Supper whiche Chriſte Ieſus made wyth hys Apoſtles. That Table is at Rome at Sainct Iohn of Latran.</p>
            <p>There is of the breade at ſainct Sauiours in Spaine. The knife wherewith the paſcal lambe was cut is at Trier: note that Chriſt Ieſus was in a borowed place whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he made his ſupper. In departing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence he left y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> table there: we do not reade y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was euer caried a way by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles. Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in a certeyn ſpace after was deſtroied:
<pb facs="tcp:13073:16"/> as we haue ſaid, what likeneſſe is there y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this table ſhould haue ben founde ſeuen or eyghte hundred yeres after? Moreouer the forme and faſhion of tables wer in thoſe dayes cleane contrary to that thei are nowe, for they dyd lye at their meales, and not ſit as it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſayde in the Goſpell. The lye then is to much manifeſt.</p>
            <p>And what lackes there more? The cuppe wherein he gaue the Sacrament of his blood to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles to drinke, is ſhewed at our Ladye of the Ile neare to Lyons, and in Albegeios in a certaine co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent of Auguſtines. Which of the two ſhall one beleue? And yet is it worſe of the platter wherein the paſcall lambe was put: for it is at Rome, at Genes, and at Earles. We muſt nedes ſaye that the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of that tyme was dyuers from ours. For where as now we haue diuers meſſes they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des haue had for one meſſe dyuers platters: Yea if one woulde geue
<pb facs="tcp:13073:16"/> credit to theſe holy reliques, wold anye man haue a more open and manifeſt falſhode?</p>
            <p>As much is to be ſayd of the lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen cloth, wherwith Ieſus Chriſt dyd wype his apoſtles feete, after that he had waſhed them. There is one at Rome at Sanct Iohn of Latran: another at Aix in Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land at ſainct Cornelius with the ſigne of Iudas fote. It muſt nedes be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the one or the other is falſe. What ſhall we then iudge? Let vs ſuffer the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to debate the matter one againſt another, vntyll ſuche tyme as one of the partyes haue verified the cauſe. In the meane tyme let vs thynke that it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but diſceyte, for to go about to make men beleue that the cloth which Ieſus Chriſt left in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe where he made his ſupper ſhoulde flye (fyue or ſyxe hundred yere af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the deſtruction of Ieruſalem) either into Italy or Dutchlande.</p>
            <p>I had forgotten the bread wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with fiue thouſand were miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſlye
<pb facs="tcp:13073:17"/> fedde in the Wylderneſſe, whereof one peece is to be ſhewed at Rome, in the church of our La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye the newe. And a lytle porcion thereof at Saincte Sauiours in Spaine.</p>
            <p>It is ſayd in the Scripture that there was a certaine porcion of Manna reſerued, for a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance that God had miraculouſly fedde the people of Iſraell in the Wildernes. But of the leauinges that were left of the fyue loaues, the Goſpell maketh no mencion that there was anye reſerued to ſuch an ende or purpoſe: and there is no auncient hiſtorye that ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth thereof, nor any Doctour of the churche. It is very eaſye to be iudged that thys (which they doe nowe ſhewe) hathe bene kned and made ſince that tyme.</p>
            <p>So muche is to be iudged of the bowe that is at Sainct Sauiours in Spayne. For they ſay that it is the ſame that Ieſus helde in hys handes when he entred into Ieru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſalem
<pb facs="tcp:13073:17"/> on Paulme Sondaye, nowe the Goſpell maketh no mencion that he dyd holde any ſuch, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is an imagined thing.</p>
            <p>Finally, we muſt place in thys rancke, another relique which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the ſelfe ſame: that is the earth whereon Ieſus Chriſt ſtode when he raiſed vp Lazarus. I prai you who was it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> marked y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place ſo well, that after the deſtruction of Ieruſalem, when all was chan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged in the countrey of Iuda, he coulde goe ſo rightlye to the place wher Ieſus Chriſt had once gone.</p>
            <p>It is time to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principal Reliques of oure Lorde Ieſus, to thoſe I meane that appertayne to his death and paſſion.</p>
            <p>And fyrſt of all let vs begynne to ſpeake of his croſſe, wherevpon he was hanged. I know that it is holden for a certaintie that it was founde of Heline the mother of Conſtantine the Romaine Empe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rour. I knowe alſo what certaine Doctours haue written touching
<pb facs="tcp:13073:18"/> the approbation hereof, for to cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie that the croſſe which ſhe fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d was without doute the ſelfe ſame on the whiche Ieſus Chriſt was hanged. Touchynge all this I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte me to the thynge it ſelfe, ſo much is there that it was but a fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh curioſitie of her, or at the leaſt a foliſhe and vnconſidered deuoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But yet put the caſe it had ben a worke worthye of prayſe to her, for to haue taken paynes to fynde the trewe croſſe, and that our lord had then declared by myracle that it was his croſſe which ſhe found: Yet let vs onely conſider that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch is of our time. Euery one doeth holde that this croſſe which He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene founde is yet at Ieruſalem, and none doeth doute thereof. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory againſt ſayeth the ſame not ablye. For it is ther recited that Helene toke one part therof to ſend to the Emperour her ſonne, who put the ſame at Conſtantinople vpon a fyne pyller of Marble in the myd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt
<pb facs="tcp:13073:18"/> of the market. Of the other part, it is ſayde that ſhe did locke the ſame in a copher of ſiluer, and gaue it the Biſhop of Ieruſalem to kepe. So then eyther we ſhall augment the hiſtorie of a lie or els that which is holden at this daye of the true Croſſe, is but a vayne and triflyng opinion.</p>
            <p>Let vs conſider on the other part howe many peeces there are ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of through out the worlde. Yf I woulde onely recite that whych I coulde ſay, there woulde be a rege<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſter ſufficient to fyl a whole boke. There is not ſo litle a town wher there is not ſome peece thereof, and that not onelye in cathedrall churchs, but alſo in ſome pariſhes Likewiſe ther is not ſo wicked an abbey where there is not of it to be ſhewed. And in ſom places ther are good great ſhydes: as at the holye chappell of Paris, and at Poiters &amp; at Rome, where there is a great crucifix made therof as men ſaye. To be ſhort, yf a man woulde ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:13073:19"/> together all that hath bene founde of thys croſſe, there would be inough to fraighte a great ſhip. The Goſpell teſtifieth that the croſſe myght be caried of one man What audacitie then was this to fyll the earth wyth peeces of wod in ſuche quantitie, that thre hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred men can not cary them? And in deede they haue forged this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe that howe muche ſo euer be cut therefrom, yet it neuer decre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth. But this a mockerye ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurde and folyſhe, that euen the ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſticious men themſelues know the contrary. I leaue them to iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge what certentie a man mai haue of all the trew croſſes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhypped here and there. I leaue to declare from whence, and by what meanes certayne peeces are come.</p>
            <p>As ſome ſaye, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which they haue hereof, was broughte them by Angels: others ſaye that it fell from heauen to them. Thoſe of Poiters ſaye that that which they haue thereof, was brought them
<pb facs="tcp:13073:19"/> by one of Helenes ladyes who had ſtolne the ſame: and as ſhe fled ſhe was founde (beyng gone aſtraye) nere vnto Poitou. Thei ad to this fable that ſhe was lame.</p>
            <p>Behold the goodly foundations they haue to perſuade the poore people to commit Idolatrye: For they haue not bene content to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue and abuſe the ſimple people in ſhewynge common wodde in ſtede of the croſſe, but thei haue re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolued that it ought to be worſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ped, which is a deuyliſhe doctrine and ſainct Ambroſe namely hath reproued it, as a Heatheneſſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſticion.</p>
            <p>After the croſſe foloweth the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle which Pilate cauſed to be put thereon, where he had written, Ieſus of Nazareth kyng of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wes. But it were requiſite that we ſhoulde knowe bothe the place and the tyme, and howe it was founde. Some wyll ſay to me that Socrates the hiſtorian of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church maketh mencion thereof. I grant
<pb facs="tcp:13073:20"/> it: But he maketh not mencion what was become therof. So then this witneſſe is of no great value nor force. Moreouer it was a wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng made in haſte and withoute conſideration, after that Ieſus Chriſt was crucified. Wherefore to ſhewe a table curiouſlye made, as it were to be kept for a ſhew, is without all reaſon therein.</p>
            <p>So then although there were but one only title, it might neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe be counterfaite falſe and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. But ſeynge the towne of Thoulouſe boſteth to haue it, and thoſe of Rome ſaye there againſt, ſhewing it in the church of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Roode: they falſecifie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one the other. Let them fight to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether then ſo much as they wyl: in the ende bothe of them ſhalbe conuicted of a lye, yf a man would examine the thing as it is.</p>
            <p>Yet there is a greater combat of the nayles. I wyll recite them onely that are come to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. Therevpon there is not ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13073:20"/> lytle a childe but wyll iudge that the Deuyll hath to much deluded the worlde in takyng from it both vnderſtandyng and reaſon, that it coulde diſcerne nothynge in thys matter. If the auncient writers ſaye trewe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi rend="roman">Hiſtoria trip. lib. 2,</hi>
               </note> and namely Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite Hiſtoriographer of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent churche, Helene cauſed one to be nayled on her ſonnes helmet, the other two ſhe put in his horſe bitte. How be it Sainct Ambroſe ſayeth not fully ſo. For he ſayeth that one was put in Conſtantins crowne, of the other his horſebit was made, and the thirde Helene kept. Wee ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> already more then twelue hundred yeres agone this hath bene in controuerſie, to wit, what was become of the nayles. What certentie can be had of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> then at thys preſent tyme.</p>
            <p>Now at Millan they boſte that thei haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nayle that was put in Conſtantines horſe bitte. To the whiche the towne of Carpentras oppoſeth her ſelfe, ſayinge that it
<pb facs="tcp:13073:21"/> is ſhe that hath it. Nowe S. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe doth not ſaye that the nayle was knit to the bitte, but that the bitte was made thereof. Whiche thyng can in no wyſe be made to agre eyther w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their ſaying of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan, or w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theirs of Carpentras.</p>
            <p>Moreouer there is one in Rome at Sainct Helenes: annother alſo in the church of the holy croſſe, an<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>other at Sene, another at Veniſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> In Germany two: at Collyne one at the three Maries: another at Triers, one in Fraunce at the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly chappell of Paris, another at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Carmes, one alſo at Sainct De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis in France: one at Burges: one at Tenaill, one at Draguigne.</p>
            <p>Beholde here fourtene, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of account is made: in euery place they alledge good approbation for them ſelues, as they ſuppoſe. And ſo it is that euerye one hath as good right as annother. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for there is no better way then to make them all paſſe vnder one fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delium. That is to ſaye, to repute
<pb facs="tcp:13073:21"/> all that they ſaye hereof to be but lyes, ſeyng that otherwiſe a man ſhoulde neuer come to an ende.</p>
            <p>There foloweth the Speare-head which can be but one: but we muſt nedes ſaye that it hath paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed throughe the fournace of ſome alcumiſte. For it is multiplied to four beſide thoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mai be in other places here and there, whereof I haue not hearde. There is one at Rome, the ſeconde at the holye chappel of Paris, the thirde in the abbey of Tenaill, at ſainct Euge: the fourth at Selne, near to Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges. Which of them nowe wyll a man chuſe for the trewe? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſhorteſt waye is to leaue them al foure for ſuch as they are. But preſuppoſe that there were but one onely, yet I would know from whence it came: For neither the auncient hiſtories, neither alſo al the other writers do make any mencion thereof. It muſt nedes be then that they were forged a new.</p>
            <p>Touchynge the crowne of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:22"/> we muſte nedes ſaye that the peeces thereof wer planted again for to grow &amp; waxe greene: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe I can not tell howe it coulde haue bene ſo augmented.</p>
            <p>For an Item, there is the third part in the holy chappell of Paris there are three thornes at Rome, in the churche of the holye Croſſe: and in the church of S. Euſtace, of Rome likewiſe ſome litle porcion: at Sene I can not tell how many thornes: at Venice one: at Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges fyue: at Beſanſon, in Saynct Iohns church thre: at Muntroyal three: at S. Sauiours in Spayne, I can not tell how many: at ſainct Iames in Galice two: at Albye three: at Tholouſe, at Maſcou, at Charoux in Poiters, at Clere, at ſainct Flour, at Sainct Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min in Prouince, in the Abbey of Salle: in the pariſhe church of S. Martin at Noyon: in euery one of theſe places ther is at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt one. If one woulde make diligent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition hereof, he might name
<pb facs="tcp:13073:22"/> foure times as many. Neceſſarily it is ſene that there is much falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode vſed herin. What confidence then may a man haue either of the one or the other? Herewith it is to be noted, that in the whole an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient church they coulde neuer tell what was become of this crowne.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it is eaſye to be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cluded, that the fyrſt plant therof beganne to budde longe tyme af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of oure Lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>There foloweth after the gonne of Purple wherewith Pilate clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched our Lorde in diriſion, for as much as he called him ſelfe a king Nowe it was a precious robe whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch was not to be caſt away: &amp; it is not to be thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pilate or his men would let it be loſt, after that he had once mocked our Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus therewith. I woulde gladlye knowe who was the marchaunt that bought it of Pilate to kepe it for a relique. But the better to cloke their deceyt: they ſhew ſome
<pb facs="tcp:13073:23"/> ſpots of bloude thereon, as if theſe wicked men woulde haue ſpylte a princely robe, in putting it by moc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kedge vpon the ſhulders of Ieſus Chriſt I know not whether there be any more in any other place. But of the garment that was wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen from top to toe without ſeme whereon lottes were caſt, becauſe that it ſemed more proper to moue the ſimple people to deuotion ther hath ben diuers fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de: for there is one at Argenteul near Paris, &amp; at Trier another. And if the bulle of Sainct Sauiours in Spaine ſayth trewe, the Chriſtians through theyr raſhe vnconſidered zeale, haue done worſe then euer did the vnfaithfull ſouldiours, for they durſt not teare it in peces, but for to ſpare it caſt lots therefore: and the Chriſtians haue torne it in pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces to worſhip it. But yet what wyll thei anſwere to the Turke, who mocketh their follye, ſaying that he hath it in hys handes. Howbeit, it is not now nedeful to
<pb facs="tcp:13073:23"/> make them plede agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Turk for it ſuffiſeth that they ende the ſtrife amonge them ſelues. The meane while we ſhalbe holden ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed thoughe we beleue neyther the one nor the other, for feare leſt we ſhoulde fauoure the one parte more then the other, wythoute knowledge of the cauſe, for that were againſt all reaſon. Moreouer if thei wold that men ſhuld beleue theyr ſayings. It is firſt of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that thei wold agre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Euan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>geliſts. Now it is ſo that this gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ment wherevpon lots were caſte, was a coat or a Iacket: which the Grekes cal <hi rend="roman">Clicoton</hi> and the Latins <hi rend="roman">tunica.</hi> Let one marke if the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Argenteul, or that of Tri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er haue ſuch a forme and faſhion. One ſhal finde it to be like a prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes cope although thei ſhould put out mens eyes, yet myghte they know their faſhold by feling with their handes. To make an ende of this article, I woulde gladly aſke a litle queſtion touching that that
<pb facs="tcp:13073:24"/> the ſouldiers did. What moued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſouldiers to deuide amongſt them the garmentes and coat of Ieſus Chriſt as the ſcripture witneſſeth It is moſt certaine that it was to ſerue them ſelues for their owne profite.</p>
            <p>Let them tell me yf they can who was that Chriſtian that boughte them of the ſouldiours, I meane as well the coat as the other gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that ar ſhewed in other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, as at Rome in the churche of Sainct Euſtace, and els where. Howe is it that the Euangeliſtes haue forgotten this? For it is an abſurde thing to ſaye that the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diours had taken in boutye the garmentes, without addyng that they were bought of them agayne at their handes for to make reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, howe is it, that all the auncient wryters, haue bene ſo ingrate to make no mencion thereof? I geue them terme to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere me to theſe queſtions,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:24"/> when men ſhall haue no moore ſence, nor vnderſtandynge to iudge.</p>
            <p>The beſt is that wyth the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they woulde alſo haue the Diſe, wherewith the lot was caſt by the ſouldyours.</p>
            <p>The one is at Trier, and two other, at Sayncte Sauyoures in Spaine. Wherein they haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed lyuely what is their folyſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: For the Euangeliſtes ſaye, that the Souldyours dyd caſte Lottes, whyche were then dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen oute of an Hatte, or oute of ſomme ſuch lyke thyng. Euen as when men chuſe the kyng of the Beane, or when as men playe at the Blancke, or at ſuch other lyke games and paſtimes.</p>
            <p>To bee ſhorte, euerye man al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte knoweth what caſtynge of Lottes meaneth: it is commonly vſed in deuydyng of partes.</p>
            <p>Theſe Beaſtes haue imagyned that the caſtynge of the Lottes, was to playe at Diſe: When they
<pb facs="tcp:13073:25"/> were not in vſage, at the leaſt ſuch as we haue it now in our time: for in ſteade of ſixe and ace and other poynctes, they had certayne mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes which thei named by theyr na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes: as Venus or dogge. Now let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that wyll go kiſſe the reliques in credite of ſo loude, playne, and manifeſt lyers.</p>
            <p>It is time to entreat of the head ſhete wherein they haue yet more plainly ſhewed as wel their impu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dencie as their folyſhenes, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the heade ſhete of the vero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicque which is ſhewed at Rome in Sainct Peters church, and the kercher that the virgyn Mary, as they ſay: put about the priuy mem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bres of our Lord, which is ſhewed at Sainct Iohn of Latrans: The whiche is alſo at the Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of Carcoſſone. Item the cloth that was put vpon his head in the ſepulchre, whiche likewiſe is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed there. There are halfe a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen townes at the leaſte, that doe boaſte to haue whole wyndynge
<pb facs="tcp:13073:25"/> ſhete of the ſepulchre. As Nice it was tranſported from Chamberie thither. Item Aix in Dutchlande. Item at Traicte: Item at Beſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: Item at Cadoin in Limoſine: Item a towne of Lorraigne, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng vpon the porte of Aſſois. Beſides the peces that are diſpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from one ſide to another. As at Sainct Sauiours in Spaine, and at the Auguſtins of Albie. I leaue oute yet a whole windyng ſhete, which is at Rome in a moneſtarie of women: becauſe that the Pope dyd forbyde to ſhew it ſolemnlye. I praye you hath not the worlde bene merueylouſlye enraged, to trot a hundred or ſixe ſcore legues longe, wyth greate charges and great paynes, for to ſee a cloute, of the which they coulde haue no certentie, but rather wer conſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned to dout thereof? for whoſouer eſtemeth or iudgeth the windyng ſhete to be in one certaine place, he maketh all the others falſe, which boſte that they haue it.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:26"/>
            <p>As for example, he that beleueth that the cloth of Chamberie is the right windynge ſhete, he condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth thoſe of Beſanſon, of Aix, of Cadoin, of Trier and of Rome, as lyers, and as them that wicked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly make the people commit Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye in deceyuyng them, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them beleue that a prophane cloth is the winding ſhete where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theyr redemer was wrapt. Let vs nowe come to the goſpell, for it wer but a ſmal matter for them to accuſe one another of a lye, but the holy ghoſt ſpeakynge agaynſt all, doeth confounde them altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther aſwell one as another.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt of all it is much meruaile that the Euangeliſtes make no mencion of this portrature that touched the face of IESVS CHRIST with a kercher: ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they make mencion of all the women that did accompany hym to the croſſe. It was a right nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thyng and worthy to be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, that the face of Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:13073:26"/> ſhould be miraculouſlye imprinted in a lynnen clothe: contrarywyſe, it ſemeth that it is but a matter of ſmall importance, to ſaye that certayne women dyd accompanye Ieſus Chriſt to the croſſe, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out there had chaunſed ſome mira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cle to them. How is it then that the Euangeliſtes rehearſe ſmale thynges and of lytle importance, holdyng their peece and makynge no mencion of principall thinges? Truly if ſuch a miracle had bene done as ſome make men to beleue we muſte needes accuſe the holye ghoſt of forgetfulneſſe, or lacke of diſcretion: that he could not chuſe prudently that which was moſte expedient for to be reported. Thus much be ſpoken touchyng the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronicque ſhete to the end that men might know what an euident and manifeſt lye it is which they wold perſuade the ſimple in.</p>
            <p>Moreouer concerning the win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng ſhete in which the body was wrapped, I aſke them a like que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:27"/> the Euengeleſtes recite dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gently y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miracles that were done at the death of Ieſus Chriſt, and do leaue nothinge out that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth to the hiſtorie: howe is it then that thys eſcaped them, that they ſpeake neuer a worde of ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cellent a miracle. To wit that the printe of the body of our Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus dyd remaine in the lynnen cloth wherein he was buried. This if it had bene ſo, was as worthy to be ſpoken of, as manye other things. Yea the holy Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt ſainct Iohn declareth, howe that Sainct Peter beyng, entred into the ſepulchre, ſaw the linnen clothes of the ſepulchre, the one of one ſide, the other on the other ſyde: but that there was anye mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous portrature, he maketh no mencion. And it is not to be thought or preſumed if there had ben any ſuch matter, that he wold haue ſuppreſſed ſuch a worke of God. There is yet another dout to be obiected: that is that the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts
<pb facs="tcp:13073:27"/> make no mencion that any of the diſciples or of the faythfull women, did cary awaye the ſhetes (wherof the queſtion is) out of the ſcripture: but rather they giue vs to vnderſtand that they left them there, although they playnely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe not the ſame. Nowe the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchre was kept with the ſouldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours. Who afterwardes had the ſhete in their owne power. Is it to be ſuppoſed or thought, that they gaue it ſome faithfull man or woman for to make reliques of? Seinge the Phariſes had corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for to make them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare them ſelues, ſaying that the diſciples had ſtolne the bodye: I leaue to reproue them of falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode, euen by the very ſight of the pictures that they ſhew. For it is eaſie to be ſene y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were payn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinges made by mans hande. And I can not merueyll ynough fyrſt, howe they were ſuch blockheads that they had no better fetch for to deceyue: and much more, how the
<pb facs="tcp:13073:28"/> worlde hath bene ſo doltiſhe, for to ſuffer it ſelfe to be blinded in ſuch ſort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it could not ſee ſo euident a thyng. Moreouer they haue well declared that they had the painter at commaundement. For when one wyndyng ſhete was burned there was alwayes another found the next daye. They woulde not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtandynge ſaye, that it was the ſelfe ſame that it was before, the which miraculouſlye was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from the fyre: but the pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng was ſo freſhe, that the lye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayled nothyng, if there had bene eies for to haue ſene and to behold But yet to make an ende wyth. There is a paremptorye reaſon, by the which they are all together conuinced of their impudencye. In all places where as they ſaye they haue the holye winding ſhete thei ſhowe a greate ſhete, whiche did conuer all the body with the head: and their in is to be ſene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> printe of a body togeather al in one pece. Nowe the Euangelyſte S. Iohn
<pb facs="tcp:13073:28"/> ſaithe, that Ieſus Chriſt was buri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed accordinge to the maner of the Iewes. And what their maner was, one maye, not onely vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande it by the cuſtume that the Iewes obſerue yeat to this daye, but alſo by their bookes, whiche ſufficiently declare the auncient cuſtume that is to binde the body a parte euen to the ſhoulders, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to wrappe the heade in a ker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chere, bindinge it at the foure cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. The which alſo the Euange<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſte expreſſeth, whan he ſayethe, that ſainct Petter ſawe the linnen clothes of one ſide wherein the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy hade bene wraped: and of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the kercher whiche was put vpon the heade for ſuch is the ſignification of this word Suaire, to take it for an hankerchere or couercheffe, and not for a greate ſhete, that ſerueth to wrape the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy in. For to conclud briefly, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Euangeliſte ſainct Iohn muſt be a lyer or els all they that boſte them ſelues to haue the win<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding
<pb facs="tcp:13073:29"/> ſhete muſt be conuicted of falſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hode, and it muſt euidentlye haue apered y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue, deaceaued the poore people, by a moſte extreme impudency it ſhould neuer be done if I wold intreate perticulerly, al the mockeries that they vſe: one dothe ſhowe at Rome at ſaincte Iohn of Latran, the rede that was put by mocking in Ieſus Chriſtes hand in ſtead of a ſepter when he was beaten in Pylates howſe.</p>
            <p>Lykewyſe at the churche of the croſſe is ſhowen the ſponge, wher the gall and myrrhe was put in his mouthe. I praye you, where is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei recouered them? It was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Infidelſes that hade them in their handes, dyde they delyuer them thinke we to the Apoſtles to make reliques of them? Or dide they the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues looke them vp, for to preſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue them for the time to come?</p>
            <p>What ſacreledge is this ſo to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>buſe the name of Ieſus Chriſt, for to cloke and couer fables ſo leude lye forged? Aſmuche is of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pence
<pb facs="tcp:13073:29"/> that Iudas receued, for betraying of our lorde.</p>
            <p>It is ſayde in the Goſpell, that he dyd render them agayne in the ſinagoge of the phariſes, and that after they bowght afylde therew<hi rend="sup">t</hi> for to burye the ſtrangers. Who is it that hathe gotten thoſe pence from the merchantes Handes. If one ſhould ſay that it was the deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, that were to folyſhe. Therfore a better coulor muſt be ſought to cloke the matter. If on ſaye that it was done longe tyme after: yet y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> were leſſe apparente, forſomuche as the mony myght haue paſſed throughe many mens handes. They muſt neades ſhowe them that either the marchante y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſolde his poſſeſſion to the phariſes for to make a buriynge place, did it for to buye the pence, to make reliques of them: or otherwyſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſold them againe to the faithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Now hereof their was neuer newes in the auncient Churche. It is a like gloſe of the ſtayres of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:30"/> Pilates Iudgement halle, whiche are at S. Iohn of latran at Rome with holes: where they ſay dropes of blood fell from the body of our lorde Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Item in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame place in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church of ſainct. Praxede, the piller wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to he was bounde, when he was ſcourged, and in the churche of the holy croſſe three others rounde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the which he was lead when he went to his death.</p>
            <p>I knowe not where they haue dreamed on all theſe pellers: ſo is it that they haue imagened them of their owne fanteſyes for in the holle hiſtorye of the Goſpell we reade nothing of them. It is ſayde that Ieſus Chriſte was whipped but that he was bonde to a peller that is of their gloſe.</p>
            <p>One maye eaſely ſee then, that they haue gone about nothing els but to heape as it were a ſeae full of lyes.</p>
            <p>Wherin they haue geuen them ſelues ſuche lybertye, that they
<pb facs="tcp:13073:30"/> haue not bene aſhamed to make a relique of the aſſes taile where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our lord Ieſus rode: for it is to be ſhowne at Genes: but we haue no more cauſe to be aſtoniſhede at their iupudencie, then at the fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſheneſſe &amp; ſtupidite of the world who hath receiued wyth great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion ſuch a deluſion. Some man might obiecte heare that it is not like that they doe ſhowe all the Reliques which we haue already named autentiklye but that they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo by &amp; by, proue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whenſe they come, &amp; out of whoſe handes they haue receaued them. To this I coulde anſwere in one worde, that in ſo euident lyes it is not poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſible to pretende any aparances of trewthe. For howe ſo euer they arme them ſelues with the name of Conſtantine, or of King Louis, or of any pope: all this aualith no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thinge, for to approue that Ieſus Chriſt was nayled with fourtene nayles: or that a hole hedge was conſumed to make hys croune of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:31"/> thornes with: or that one Speare blade ſhuld haue ingendrede ſince, thre others: or that his cotte ſhuld be multiplied into thre, and haue chaunged faſhion for to become a priſtes: coope or that of on onelye windinge ſhete their ſhould haue ſpronge a broode as it were the Chikennes of one Henne: that IESVS CHRIST was buryed cleane contraye to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that the Ghoſpell mencyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth.</p>
            <p>If I ſhoulde ſhowe a Lumpe of leade, and ſhoulde ſaye. This Lumpe of Golde was geuen me by ſuch a prince, I ſhoulde be eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temed for a mad foole, and for my ſaying the leade wold not change his colour, nor his nature for to be changed into golde. So when they ſay to vs, behold what God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frey of Bullon did ſende hether, after he had conquered the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Iude: and that reaſon doth declare vnto vs, that it is but a lye: ſhoulde we ſuffer our ſelues
<pb facs="tcp:13073:31"/> to be abuſed wyth the wordes, and not beholde that whyche we ſee before our eyes?</p>
            <p>But yet, to thende that we may knowe howe ſure it is to truſte to all that they aledge for the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of their reliques: it is to be noted that the principall Relyques and the moſte notable that be at Rome were brought thi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther (as they ſaye) by Tytus and Vaſpaſian.</p>
            <p>Trewlye it is as playne a moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedge, as if one ſhoulde ſaye that the Turke wente to Ieruſalem, for to ſeeke the holye Croſſe of IESVS CHRIST to the ende to place it at Conſtantin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople.</p>
            <p>Vaſpaſian, before he was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Emperour conquered and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed part of Iude afterwardes, when he came to the Empyre he lefte hys ſonne Titus to be hys Leutenant, who afterwards won the citie of Ieruſalem.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:32"/>
            <p>Nowe theſe were heathen, who cared or ſet as muche by Ieſus Chriſte as by him that neuer had bene. So one may iudge whether they durſt not as frely lye in alled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyng Godfrey of Bullon or ſainct Louys, as they haue alledged Vaſpaſien.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, let it be conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red what iudgement as well the kyng had (whome they call ſainct Louys, as all other ſuch like had. He had in dede (ſuch as it was) a de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uotion &amp; zeale for to augment chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtendome: but if one ſhoulde haue ſhewed them goates dunge, and haue ſaide to them beholde here be our Ladyes Beades: they woulde without any agayne ſaying haue worſhipped them, or woulde haue brought them hyther in their ſhip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes for to haue ſet them vp hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably in ſom place: and i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> very dede they haue conſumed their bodies &amp; their goods &amp; a great part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtaunce of their countrey, for to bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ouer an heape of ſmal trifles,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:32"/> wherewith they were brought in a fooles Paradiſe, thinkinge that they were the moſte precious Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wels in the worlde. But yet to geue more ample vnderſtandynge of this matter, it is to be noted, that in all Grecia and the leſſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, and Mauritania, whyche we nowe commonly call the countrey of Iude, they ſhew with great aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuraunce al theſe antiquities, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch the poore Idolatours that be about vs thynke that they haue. What is to be iudged betwen the one and the other? We ſhall ſaye the reliques were broughte vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe countreys. The Chriſtians that yet remain ther, affirme that they haue them: and deride our fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe boſtyng. How ſhould one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide thys proceſſe without an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition, which can not be made, nor neuer wilbe made? wherfore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only remedy is to leaue the thyng as it is, not caryng neither for the one part nor for the other.</p>
            <p>The laſte reliques that apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain
<pb facs="tcp:13073:33"/> to Ieſus Chriſt are thoſe that they haue had ſince his reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: as a morſell of a broyled fyſhe which ſainct Peter preſented him when he appeared to hym on the border of the ſea. We muſt nedes ſay that it was wel ſpiced, or that it was merueylouſly well ſouſſed that it coulde be preſerued ſo long a time. But withoute laughter it is to be thought that the Apoſtles made a relique of the fiſhe which they had prepared for their dyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? Whoſoeuer ſhall not ſee that this is a manifeſt and open moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedge of God, I leaue him as a beaſt, which is not worthye that one ſhoulde teache hym anye fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Ther is alſo the miraculous blood which iſſued out of the cake Gods as at Paris in ſainct Iohns churche, at Dion at Sainct Iohn the Euangeliſts church and elles where in many places. And to the ende they might make the heape more greater, they haue ioyned thereto the holye penknife where
<pb facs="tcp:13073:33"/> with our maiſter of Querne was not content: but did reproch them that thei were worſe then Iewes: For aſmuche as they did worſhip the knife, that had bene an inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to violate the precious bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye of Ieſus Chriſte. The which I alledge, becauſe as much might be ſayde of the ſpeare, nayles, and thornes. That is that al they that worſhyppe them (according to our mayſter of Quernes ſentence) are more wycked then the Iewes, who crucified our Lord. Likewiſe they ſhewe the forme and prynt of his fete, where he marched whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he appeared to certaine of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples after his aſcention, as there is one at Rome in Sainct Lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence church in the place where he met Sainct Peter, when he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhewed him y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhoulde ſuffer at Rome. Another at Poiters at S. Raguonde another at Soiſon, an other in Arles. I diſpute not wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ieſus Chriſt coulde haue im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed the fourme and faſhion of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:34"/> his fete on a ſtone. But I only diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute of the facte, and I ſaye, that ſeyng there is no lawfull probati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hereof, all this ought to be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted for a fable. But the moſt beaſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly relique of this kynde is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> forme of his hippes which is at Reins in Champania, vpon a ſtone behynd the hyghe aultare. And they ſaye that thys was done at ſuch tyme as oure Lorde became a Maſon, for to buylde their church porche. This blaſphemie is ſo execrable that I am aſhamed to ſpeake any more thereof. Let vs then paſſe further, and let vs ſe what is ſaid of his images: I mean not of them which are comonly made by pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſtonegrauers or Ioyners, for the number of them is infinite: but of thoſe which haue a certayn ſpecial dignitie for to be kept, and contende with ſome ſingularitie as reliques. Now hereof there are two ſortes: Some were made miraculouſlye: As that whiche is ſhewed at Rome in Sayncte
<pb facs="tcp:13073:34"/> Maries churche, that they call in Poeticu. Item another at S. Iohn of Latrans. Item another where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is drawen his picture at the age of .xii. yeres. Item that of Lukes which the ſaye was made by the angels &amp; which thei cal vultus ſan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctus. Theſe are ſuch fonde vayne fables y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſemeth to me it ſhoulde be loſt labour, yea &amp; that it ſhould be rediculous and foliſhe if I dyd occupy my ſelfe therein. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it ſufficetth to haue noted them by the way for men knowe ryghte well that thys is not the exerciſe or vocation of angels to to be paynters: and that our lorde Ieſus wyll otherwiſe be knowen of vs and brought into oure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce then by carnal ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. Euſebius in dede writeth in the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtorie that he ſent a lyuelye Printe of hys vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to kynge Abagarus but this is as certaine and of as much cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit as one of kyng Meluſines com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandementes in his chronicles.
<gap reason="missing" extent="2 pages">
                  <desc>〈2 pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:13073:35"/> and foliſhe that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt part count this as certaine as the Ghoſpel. I place alſo in this ranke the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes, that haue ſpoken, wherof the multitude is great but let vs be content with one for an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. To witte, with that of ſainct Denis in Fraunce. It ſpake ſaye they, for to beare witneſſe that the church was dedicated I leaue it to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered whether y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thing were worthe ſo much. But yet I aſke them, howe is it that the cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifix could be then in the Church, ſeing that when men wil dedicate them they remoue all the Images howe ſtale it then away or hide it ſelfe to the ende it myght not be caried awaye with the others we muſt neades ſaye y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they thoughte to deceaue the world at their plea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure, ſeing that they haue not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red manifeſtly to contrarye them ſelues but that it hathe ſuffyſed them: to lye with open mouth not regardinge what men mygth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply agaynſt them. There remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth
<pb facs="tcp:13073:35"/> laſt of all the teares: wherof one is at Vandoſme, one at Trier one at ſaynct Maxymyn, one at ſainct peters in Orleans, beſydes them that I knowe not. Some, as they ſay, are naturall, as that of ſainct Maximin, which according to their Chronicles, fell from our Lord Ieſus whileſt he waſhed his Apoſtles fete: the reſidue are miraculous. As thoughe it were to be beleued, that the woden cru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifixes were ſo greued or ſorowful that they ſhoulde weape. But we muſt parde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them this faught. For they were aſhamed that theyr I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles, ſhoulde not doe aſmuch as thoſe of the heathen. Nowe the heathen haue fained that theyr I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolles did wepe certain times.</p>
            <p>Wherfore we maye right well put them together. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the viergen Mary, forſomuch as they holde that her bodye is no more in yearthe, the meane for to boſt themſelues to haue her bones is taken awaye. From them. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe
<pb facs="tcp:13073:36"/> I thynke, they woulde haue made the world beleue, that ſhe had had a body ſufficent to fell a great poudryng fatte. Moreouer they haue venged them ſelues vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her heare, and on her milke for to haue ſome parte of her bodye. There is of her heare at Rome at ſainct Maries Churche vpon mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne, at ſainct Sauiour i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Spaine at Maſcon, at Cluny, at Noers, at ſainct Flour, at S Iaqueries, and in many others places: tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the mylke is not nowe nead full to number the places where ther is of it neither ſhuld we come to any ende therof for their is not ſo littell a towne, nor ſo wicked a conuent be it of monckes or be it of Nones, wher ſome percell ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is not ſhowed ſome more, ſome leſſe not that they were not aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to boſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues to haue had holle potte fulls, but for aſmuche as thei thought that their lie ſhuld be the more couered. They haue therfore Inuented to ſhewe onely
<pb facs="tcp:13073:36"/> aſmuch therof as might be kept in a glaſſe to the ende men might ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>amen it no nearer. So that if the holye virgyne hadde bene a cowe, or that ſhe had bene a norſe al her life time, yet could ſhe not ſcarſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue geuen ſuche quantetye of milke: on the other part, I would gladly aſke them, how this milke whych at this preſent daye is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed almoſt throughout the world was geathered, for to be preſerued vntyll our tyme. For we doe not reade that euer anye had thys cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioſitye. It is well ſayde that the ſhepherdes dyde worſhype Ieſus Chriſte, and that the wiſe men did offer to him their preſentes: but it is not ſaide that thei did carie back mylke for a recompence? Saynct luke recitethe that which Simeon did foreſhewe the virgine, but he ſayeth not that he aſked of her milke. If one ſhoulde conſider but onely this point, it ſhoulde not be nedefull to argue any further for to declare how greatly thys folly
<pb facs="tcp:13073:37"/> is againſt al reaſon, and without all kind of coniecture and cloke. And it is meruell (ſeing thei could haue no other part of her body) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue not bene auyſed of the paring of her nayles, and of ſuche other like thinges: But it is to be thought that they haue not had al in their remembraunce. The reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reliques which thei haue of our Lady, is of her baggage or clothes. There is one of her ſmoc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes at Chartres, of the which one doth make an Idoll ſufficiently re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nomed. And there is another at Aix in Dutchland. I leaue them there, to wit, how thei could haue gotten them. For it is a thynge moſte certaine, that the Apoſtles and the trewe Chriſtians of their time, haue not bene ſo doltiſhe as for to occupy their mindes vpon ſuche vayne trifles. But let one beholde onely the fourme and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion thereof, and I wyll quite the play, if in beholdyng it one do not playnly ſee their impudencie.
<pb facs="tcp:13073:37"/> When one doth ſhewe the ſmoke, (which we haue ſayde to be at Aix in Dutchlande:) one doth ſhew at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ende of a pole, as it were a long white ſurplice of a prieſt. Nowe if the virgine Mary had bene a gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aunt yet coulde ſhe ſcarcely haue worne ſo great a ſmok. And for to make a better ſhew therof, one do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th cary ſtraight wayes after the li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle hoſe of Sainct Ioſeph, which are lytle ynough for a lytle childe or for a darfe. The prouerbe ſayth that a lyer ought to haue a good memory, for feare of tripping him ſelf by forgetfulnes. Thei haue al obſerued this rule, when thei haue not thought or inuented to make better proporcion of the huſbands hoſe &amp; the wiues ſmoke. Let men now goe and kiſſe deuoutly theſe reliques, the which haue no other appearance of truth. As touching her kerchers I know but two: one at Trier in Maximins abbey: ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther at Liſio in Italie. But I woulde that one ſhoulde marke of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:38"/> what linnen they are, and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they did weare that kynde of faſhion at that time in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Iuda. I woulde alſo that men ſhoulde make compariſon of them, for to ſee howe like they be the one to the other. At Reuline they haue as it were a browe. Some peraduenture wil aſke me, if I think that this brow be a cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfaite thing. I anſwere that I eſteme it as muche as her gyrdle, which is at Prat, and as that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch is at oure Ladyes of Montſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret. Item of her ſlypper, which is at Sainct Iaqueries, and one of her ſhowes, which is at Saincte Flour. If there were no other but this thing yet all men of meane wiſedome may knowe right well that it was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maner or vſe of the faithfull to gather in ſuch ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and ſorte hoſe and ſhowes for to make reliques: and moreouer there was neuer mencion hereof made, aboue the ſpace of fyue hun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dred yeres after the death of the
<pb facs="tcp:13073:38"/> virgin Mary. What nede we then argue herevpon any longer, as yf the thynge were doutfull? Yea, thei woulde make the holy virgin beleue, that ſhe was very curious to decke &amp; trim her ſelfe. For they ſhewe two of her comes. One at Rome, in ſaint Martyns churche: and another in the church of ſaint Iohn the great of Beſanſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſydes them which myghte be ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed other where. If thys be not to mocke the holy virgyn Mary, I know not what mockedge is. Thei haue not alſo forgotten her weddyng ryng: for they haue it at Peruſe. Becauſe now the cuſtome is, that the huſbande ſhould gyue his wyfe a weddynge rynge: they haue imagyned that it was the vſe at that time. And without ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kyng further inquiſition, they haue ordeyned and made a riche and coſtly ryng to thys vſe, not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſidering in what pouertie the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly virgyne lyued. There is of her gounes at Rome at S. Iohn of La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tran.
<pb facs="tcp:13073:39"/> Item at S. Barbares chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che. Item at ſainct Maries vpon Mineru e. Item, at ſainct Blaſe churche. At ſainct Sauiours in Spaine. At the leaſt they ſay they haue certaine pieces. I haue hard of many other places: But they are not in my memorie. To de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and ſhowe the falſhede here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of it is onlye requiſite to marke well the matter, for they haue thought it as eaſie to them for to attribute ſuch kinde of veſtments at their pleaſure to the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, as for to clothe the images in ſuch ſort as they clothe them.</p>
            <p>It reſteth to entreate of images not of the common ſort, but of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that are in eſtimation aboue the others, by a certaine ſingularitie. Now they woulde make S. Luke beleue that he paynted foure of thoſe they call inuiolata at Rome in the place where nowe Sainct Maries churche ſtandeth, one of them is ſhewed in an oratory: the which as they ſay he made in his
<pb facs="tcp:13073:39"/> deuotion, with the ring wherwith Ioſeph wedded her. There is ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther ſhewed likewiſe at Rome at the new ſainct Maries, the which thei ſay was alſo made by Sainct Luke in Troades, and that ſince that time it was brought to them by an angell. Item another at S. Maries Araceli, in ſuche likenes as ſhe was when ſhe ſtode by the croſſe. But they of ſainct Auguſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes boſte them ſelues to haue the chiefe and principall: for it is it (if one beleue them) that ſainct Luke caryed alwayes w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> him, euen vntil he made it to be buried i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his graue I praye you, what blaſphemye is this to make a holy eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt a ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifeſt &amp; perfect idolater? &amp; likewiſe what colour or cloke haue thei for to perſuade men y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> S. Luke was a painter. S. Paul wel calleth him a Phiſition, but of paynters craft I know not where they haue drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med it. And though it were he had bene ſkilde in the occupation: yet not wythſtandynge it is as lykely to be thought, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he woulde
<pb facs="tcp:13073:40"/> haue had paynted the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye as Iupiter or Venus, or any other Idol. It was not the maner of Chriſtians to haue images? nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath it bene of longe tyme af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, vntill ſuch tyme as the church was corrupted with ſuperſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. On the other part al the quarters almoſt of the worlde are full of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages of the virgin Mary, which ſome do ſay he made, as at Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, and here and there. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what ſorte and forme are they paynted? There is aſmuch hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie and comlynes as if one would picture a diſſolute woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Behold how god hath blinded them, that they haue had no more conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on then brute beaſtes. But I am not greatly aſtoniſhed in that thei haue imputed to S. Luke for to haue made Images of the virgine ſeyng they haue bene ſo bolde to impute the lyke vnto the prophet Ieremy. I can witnes the ſame in Auuergnie. It ſhoulde be time (as I thinke) that the worlde woulde
<pb facs="tcp:13073:40"/> once open her eyes, for to ſee that which is ſo manifeſt. I leaue to ſpeake of S. Ioſeph, of whom ſom haue his ſlippers, as in S. Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s abbey of Trier. Other ſome (as we haue already ſaid) his hoſe: o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers alſo his bones. The exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple which I haue already alledged ſuffiſeth me for the diſcouering of the foliſhnes that is therein. I wil place S. Mihell here, to the ende he may accompany the virgin Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. Some will thinke that I do as it were ieſt or mock, in rehearſing the reliques of an Angell. Yea the abuſers them ſelues haue mocked them: but they haue not therfore letted to abuſe in good earneſt the poore people: For at Carcaſſone they boſt to haue certain reliques of him, &amp; likewiſe at S. Iulians of Tours. They do ſhow at great S. Mihels (which is ſo well haun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of pilgrimes) his ſworde whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch is like a childs dagger, and his buckler likewiſe which is as it were the boſſe of an horſe bitte.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:41"/>
            <p>There is neither man nor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſo ſimple, who may not iudge what mockerye this is. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſuche lyes are conuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſhadowe of deuotion, it ſemeth that it is not ill done for to mocke God, and his Angelles. Thei wil alledge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcripture witneſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſainct Mihell dide fyght againſt the Diuell but if it hade bene re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that he ſhoulde haue ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the diuell with the ſworde it was neadfull that he ſhould haue had one more ſtronger, better poin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted and of a better blade, then that is. Are they ſuch beaſtes to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine that it was a carnall combat which is foughte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> material ſword which aſwell the Angelles as the faythfull haue agaynſt the diuells? But it is as I haue ſayde in the begeninge: that the worlde worthelie dede deſerue to be decea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued in ſuch beſtlineſſe: forſomuch as it was ſo peruerſſe for to couet to worſhip vaine Idolles &amp; mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mettes in ſtead of worſhiping the liuing God for keapeng of order
<pb facs="tcp:13073:41" rendition="simple:additions"/> It is now requiſit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treat of S. Iohn Baptiſt: who (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Euangelicall hiſtori) after he was beheded, was buried by his diſciples. Theodorit an aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient cronicler of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church mencio<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſepulchre being in Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſte, a towne of Siria was ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (a certain time after) by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his bones were burned by them &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſhes eſparſſed in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aire. Albeit that Euſebe addeth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyn men of Ieruſalem chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed to come thither, &amp; ſecrettly toke ſome litel part, which was caried to An<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tioche &amp; ther buried. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his head, Sozomenus an other cro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicler ſaith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was caried away by Theodoſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> emperor, neare to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> citie of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantinoble. Wherefore according to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ancient hiſtories al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole body was burned except y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> head: &amp; al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bones &amp; the aſhes loſt, except ſom certen litel portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hermites of Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtale fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thenſe let vs ſe what is now fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d. They of Amiens boſte themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to haue the viſage and in the
<pb facs="tcp:13073:42"/> maſke which they ſhewe, there is the ſigne of the cut of a knife ouer whart the eye, which they ſay He<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rodias gaue him. But they of S. Iohn of Angel ſay there agaynſt, and doe ſhowe the like parte. As concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt of the head from the crowne to the forehead was at Rhodes: and is nowe at Malte as I thinke. At the leaſt they haue made men beleue that the Turke did render it them. The hinder parte is at S. Iohn of Nemours: the braine is at Noyon. Beſides all this, they of S. Iohn of Mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en doe not wante ſome certayne parte of the head: his chawes are ſene at Beſanſon at ſainct Iohn y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great: there is another part at S. Iohn of Latrans at Paris, and at S. Flour in Auuergne. Thei kepe his heare at ſainct Sauiours in Spaine, the brow and ſome of the heare: There is alſo ſome lytle iote thereof at Noyon, which is ſhowen very autentikly. There is alſo ſome part (I knowe not of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:42"/> what place) at ſainct Lukes. Is al this done? Let one goe to Rome, and to the moneſtary of ſaint Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſter, and one ſhall heare beſides ſayde: beholde here is ſainct Iohn Baptiſtes head. The Poetes fain that there was in tyme paſſed a king in Spaine, named Gereon, who had three heades. If our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique forgers coulde ſaye as much of ſainct Iohn Baptiſt, this wold ſerue well for their purpoſe, to helpe them to lye. But ſeing thys fable hath no place, how wyl they excuſe them ſelues? I wyll not preſſe them ſo neare, as for to aſke them howe the head was ſo hac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, for to be parted in ſo manye places, and ſo diuerſlye: neyther howe they haue gotten the ſame from Conſtantinople: but I onely ſaye, that ſainct Iohn muſt nedes be a monſter, or that they be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhame faſt abuſers, for to ſhewe ſo many peeces of his head. And whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch is more they of Sene boſte to haue his arme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant
<pb facs="tcp:13073:43"/> to all the auncient hiſtories. And yet neuertheleſſe this abuſe is not only ſuffered but alſo appro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued as in dede nothinge is founde euel to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kingdome of Antichriſte prouiding that it intertaine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple in ſuperſtition. Nowe they haue inuented an other fable that is, when al the body was burned that the finger wherewith he dyd pointe and ſhewe our Lord Ieſus dide remayne hole not beyng con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed. This, not only, is not con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formable to the auncient hiſtories but it may alſo eaſely be reproued by them for Euſebe, &amp; Theodorite plainly ſay that the body (when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> payens reueſhed it) was alreadye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſemed to bones. And they would in no wiſe haue forgotten ſuche a miracle if their had bene any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at all for they are but ouermuche curiouſſe in mencioninge of vaine and trifeling thinges.</p>
            <p>Not withſtandinge althoughe it hade bene ſo, yet let vs heare in howe manye places thys fynger
<pb facs="tcp:13073:43"/> is. There is one at Beſanſon in the church of ſaint Iohn the great another at Lions, another at Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges, at Florence another, another at Saincte Iohn of Aduentures neare to Maſcon.</p>
            <p>I ſaye nothyng herevpon except y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I praye the gentle readers not to harden theyr hartes agaynſt ſuch a cleare and certayne aduertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that they woulde not ſhutte theyr eyes, to ſuche a clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, for to lette them ſelues al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways to be deceiued as in darknes</p>
            <p>Yf that Iugglers ſhoulde haue had ſo blynded our eyes that we ſhoulde thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there was ſyxe, yet ſhoulde we bee thus mynded for to feare to be abuſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued.</p>
            <p>But herein is no ſubteltie, for queſtion is onely made wheather we wyl beleue that Sainct Iohns fynger is at Flourence, and that thei be alſo other where i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fiue pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as at Lyons at Burges and other places.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:44"/>
            <p>For to ſpeake more brieflye, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we will beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſixe fingers are but one, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> one finger only is ſixe. I ſpeake but onely of that which is come to my knowledge. I dout not but if that one ſhoulde enquire more diligentlye, there ſhoulde be at the leaſt founde one half douſen more in other places. And that their ſhuld not be found yet other peeces, which woulde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounte to the bignes of a bulles head, yea beſides thoſe which I haue named. But for feare of lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing any thyng behind, thei haue likewiſe boſted to haue the aſhes: wherof one part is at Gines, the other part at Rome in S. Iohn of Latrans church: Nowe we haue ſene that the moſt part was caſte into the aire: yet neuertheleſſe they let not to haue (as they ſaye) a great part and chiefely they of Genes.</p>
            <p>There remayneth nowe after the bodye the other appertenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as one of his ſhowes, which
<pb facs="tcp:13073:44"/> is at the charter houſe of Paris: the whiche was ſtolne aboute twelue or thyrtyne yeres ago: but there was a newe one founde incontinently. And in dede vntyll ſhowmakers ſcience fayle, they wyll neuer wante ſuche reliques. At Rome at ſainct Iohn of La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trans, they boſte to haue his iacketh: whereof no mencion is made in the goſpell, except becauſe it is there ſpoken, that he was clothed with camelles heare, they woulde chaunge a gowne into a iacket.</p>
            <p>There lykewiſe they ſaye they haue the Aultar whereon he prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Deſarte: as yf in thoſe dayes they dyd vſe to make Aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars for euery purpoſe and in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry place.</p>
            <p>It is meruayll they make them not beleue that he ſonge Maſſe. In Auignon is the ſworde wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he was beheaded. And at Aix in Dutchlande is the lynnen clothe that was ſpreadde vnder hym. I woulde gladly know how
<pb facs="tcp:13073:45"/> the hangman was ſo gracious and fauourable, as for to tapiſtrie the pauement of the priſon, when he would put him to death. Is not this a foliſh inuencion? But yet, how is either the one or the other com to their hands? do you thinke it to be likely, that he which put him to death, whether he were a ſouldiour or a hangman, woulde haue geuen away the linnen cloth and his ſworde for to make reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques of them? Seing they woulde make ſuche a furniture of all pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they haue fayled in leauing &amp; forgettyng Herodias knife, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with ſhe ſtrake him vpon the eye lidde. Likewiſe all the bloud that was ſpylt, and alſo his ſepulchre. But I maye well erre herein: for I know not if all thoſe baggages be other where els. It is nowe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite that the Apoſtles ſhoulde haue their courſe: but becauſe the multitude myghte engender con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion, if I ſhoulde place them all together: we wyll firſt ſpeake of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:45"/> ſainct Peter and ſainct Paule, then after we wyll ſpeake of the others.</p>
            <p>Theyr bodyes are at Rome, one halfe in ſainct Peters Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and the other halfe at ſainct Paules Church: And they ſaye, that ſainct Silueſter did parte them, for to diſtribute them in ſuch equall porcions.</p>
            <p>Their two heades are at Rome at Sainct Iohn of Latrans: al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in the ſame churche there is one of ſayncte Peters teeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone by it ſelfe. Beſydes al thys, they doe not lette to haue euerye where theyr bones. As at Poiters they haue the chawe bone with the beard. At Trier diuers bones bothe of the one and of the other: At Argenton in Bery one of ſaint Paules ſhoulders.</p>
            <p>But when ſhoulde this be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded? For in euerye place wheare there is a Churche that dothe beare theyr names, there are alſo of their reliques. If one doe aſke
<pb facs="tcp:13073:46"/> what relikes? Let them remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the brayne of ſainct Peter, whereof I haue ſpoken, whyche was on the greate Aultar of thys towne. For euen as that was founde to be a marble ſtone, ſo ſhall men finde many horſe bones or dogge bones, that they do attri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bute to theſe two apoſtles. With the body there foloweth the other appertenaunce. At ſainct Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in Spaine they haue one of ſainct Peters ſlippers but of the faſhion, and the thing whereof it is made, I can make no mencion, but it is to be ſuppoſed that it is ſuch like marchandiſe as that whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch is at Poiters: The whiche are made of Satynne brodered wyth golde. Beholde howe braue they do make him after his death, for to recompenſe him of the pouertie wherein he liued durynge his lyfe tyme. Becauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhops in theſe dayes are ſo trim, when thei decke them with their pontifical robes. It ſemeth to them that one ſhuld
<pb facs="tcp:13073:46"/> abrogate the apoſtles dignitie, yf he did not make them as trim, for painters maye well counterfaite them at their pleaſure, gyldyng and adorning them from the head to the fete, and afterward put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them the names of Peter and Paule: but we knowe what their eſtate was whileſt thei lyued in this world, and that they had no other then poore mennes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>There is alſo at Rome the po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call chere of ſainct Peter with his coope. As if in thoſe dayes the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had had thrones for to ſytte in: their office was to teache coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell, and exhorte bothe publiklye and peculierly, and to ſhewe good example of true humilitie to their flocke: and not to make ydolles, as thoſe that are now a dayes do. As co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning his cope, it was not yet in thoſe dayes the faſhion or maner ſo to diſguyſe them ſelues: for they did not playe the kynde of Maſkers in the Churche as
<pb facs="tcp:13073:47"/> they do at this preſent.</p>
            <p>So that for to proue that ſaynct Peter had a cope, it is fyrſt requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that they ſhoulde declare S. Peter to be a Iugler, as our prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes nowe a dayes doe, ſemyng to ſerue God. It is trewe that they maye well haue geuen him a cope when thei aſſigned him an aulter. But as lykelye is the one as the other. Men do knowe what Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes were ſonge at that tyme.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles dyd celebrate ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plye in their tyme the ſupper of our Lorde: to the which, it is not nedefull to haue an aulter.</p>
            <p>They did not knowe yet at that tyme what beaſt this Maſſe was: Neyther was it knowen longe tyme after.</p>
            <p>One maye euidentlye ſee then that when they inuented their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques they neuer douted that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they ſhould haue any ſpeakers there againſt, ſeyng they haue ben bolde to lye ſo impudently &amp; wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonly. Moreouer as touching this
<pb facs="tcp:13073:47"/> aulter they agre not among them ſelues: For they of Rome affirme that they haue it, and thei of Piſe likewiſe ſay thei haue it, ſhewing it alſo in theyr ſubburbes, that ſtande towardes the ſea. For to make theyr profit of all, they haue not forgotten the ſworde where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with Maulchus eare was cut of: as if it had bene a Iewell worthy to be made a relique. I had forgot<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten his Croiſier the which is ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen at ſainct Steuen of Grees at Paris: of the which is to be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med as much as of the aulter, or of the cope: for it ſtandeth wyth lyke reaſon.</p>
            <p>There is a lytell more apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce of his weapon. For it may well be preſuppoſſed or thought y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he myght (goynge by the fyeldes) be armed with ſuche a ſtaffe.</p>
            <p>But thei marre all, in that they can not agree: For they of Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logne fermeli maintaine that they haue it, &amp; likewiſe they of Tryer: ſo in beliyng the one the other, thei
<pb facs="tcp:13073:48"/> geue good occaſion that one ſhuld beleue neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both. I leaue to ſpeake of ſainct paulles chaine, wherwith he was bound, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is ſhewen at Rome in his church. Item, of the peller, wheron ſainct peter was marterede, the which is at ſainct Anaſtaſe. I leaue only to the readers to Iudge. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence this chaine was gotten, for to be made a relique: Item, to wit if in thoſe daies the maner were to put men to death vpon pillers.</p>
            <p>We will Ioyntly intreate of all the other Apoſtles for to make an ende the ſonner. And firſt of al we will rehearſe where there is holle bodyes, to the ende that in confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the one to the other, one may iudge what ſure holde may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of their ſayinges. Euery one dothe knowe that the towne of Thoulouſe thinketh to haue the ſyxt: to wit, ſainct Iames the greater, ſainct Andrew, ſainct Ia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes leſſer, ſainct Philippe, ſainct Simon and ſainct Iude. At padue
<pb facs="tcp:13073:48"/> is ſainct mathias body, at Salerne ſainct Matthewes bodi at Ortone ſainct Thomas body, in the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Naples, S. Barthelmews bodye. Let vs nowe marke whiche of them haue two, or thre, bodyes Sainct Andrewe hath a ſecond bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy at Melphe: ſainct Philipe, and ſainct Iames the leſſer, eache of them alſo an other body at Rome in ſainct Peters Churche: ſaincte Barthelmew alſo another at Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>e in hys Churche. And yet aboue all this, the ſkinne of ſainct Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thelmew is at Piſe. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinge ſainct Mathias is aboue all the others: For he hath a ſeconde bodye at Rome, in the Churche of ſainct Marye the greater, and a thirde bodye at Trier. Beſydes this, he hath a head and an arme, aparte likewiſe at Rome. It is trew that the lightell peices of S. Andrewe, which are heare, and there, If they were put together behalfe as muche: for at Rome in ſainct peters Churche, there is a
<pb facs="tcp:13073:49"/> head, in ſainct Griſogone a ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, at ſainct Euſtacea ſide, at the holy ghoſts church an arme, I can not tel what other part at Blaiſe at Aix in prouince a fote. Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer ſhoulde ioyne theſe together it woulde be inough for to make two whole quarters, prouidynge that one could wel proportion the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Now as S. Bartelmewes ſkinne is at Piſe, ſo is one of his handes there: At Trier there is I knowe not what membre, at Freius a fin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ger, at Rome in ſainct Barbares church, other reliques. So yet he is not one of the pooreſt, for the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue not ſo muche: Albeit that euerye one hath yet ſome ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle parte.</p>
            <p>As Sayncte Phylyppe hathe a foote at Rome, at the holye Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and at Saynct Barbares I can not name what reliques. Item more at Trier. In theſe two laſt Churches he hath Sainct Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for his companio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Who hath likewyſe in ſainct Peters church
<pb facs="tcp:13073:49"/> his head, and an arme at Sainct Griſogone, another at the holye Apoſtles. Sainct Mathewe and Saynct Thomas haue remayned the moſte pooreſt.</p>
            <p>For the fyrſte wyth his bodye hath but onely certayne bones at Trier, an arme at Rome, at ſainct Marcell, and at ſaynct Nicolas a head. Vnleſſe peraduenture ſome thynge haue eſcaped me, whych maye well be done, for in ſuche a darkeneſſe who ſhall not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed? Becauſe they fynde in their Chronicles that the body of ſainct Iohn the Euangeliſt dyd vaniſhe away incontinently after it was putte in the Graue: They coulde not brynge forthe anye of hys bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. But for the ſupplyinge of thys want, they caſt themſelues vpon his baggage.</p>
            <p>And fyrſte of all, they haue bene aduiſed of the Chalice, in whiche he drancke the Poyſon, beynge condempned by Domician. But for aſmuche as two wyll haue it,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:50"/> either we muſt beleue that which the alchumiſtes ſaye of their mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: or that theſe with their chalice, haue mocked the worlde. The one is at Bullin, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Rome at ſainct Iohn of La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tran. They haue afterwardes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented to haue founde his Iacket, and the chaine wherewith he was bound when thei led him priſoner from Epheſus: with the oratorye wherein he accuſtomed to praye being in priſon. I woulde gladlye know if there were at that tyme, hired Ioiners for to make him ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tories. Item what familiaritie or acquaintance the chriſtians had w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his kepers for to withdrawe the chaine for to make it a relique. Theſe mockeries are ouer muche foliſhe, yea if thei were to deceyue litle children with. But the moſte eſtemed iewell is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> twelue comes of the apoſtles, which thei do ſhew at our lady of the yle neare Lions I thinke thei were placed there at the beginning, for to make men
<pb facs="tcp:13073:50"/> beleue that they were the comes of the .xii. fathers of Fraunce: but ſince their dignitie hath increaſed and they are become apoſtolicke. We muſt from henceforth haſten or otherwiſe we ſhoulde neuer go out of this foreſt.</p>
            <p>We wyll then brieflye recite the reliques that they haue of the ſainctes, which were in the time that Ieſus Chriſt liued: then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentlye of the auncient mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, and of other ſainctes. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon the reader ſhal haue occaſion to iudge what eſtimacion they oughte to haue. Sainct Anne mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the virgin Mary hath one of her bodies at Apte in Prouince the other at our lady of the yle at Lions. Beſides this ſhe hath one head at Trier: the other at Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, another at Turinge in a towne named after her name. I leaue the pieces which ar in more then a hundred places: and amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt all others I remembre that I haue kiſt one part in the abbey of
<pb facs="tcp:13073:51"/> Orcaps neare Noyon where they make great feaſtyng. Finally ſhe hath one of her armes at Rome in ſainct Paules churche. Let them proue the fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacion therof if they can. There foloweth after Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus and Magdeline his ſiſter. As touching him, he hath as farre as I know but thre bodies, one is at Merſels, the other at Authum, the thyrd at Aualon. It is true that they of Authum haue had great proces againſt them of Aualon. But after that bothe parties had ſpent much money, thei haue both of them won their cauſe: at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt they remaine in poſſeſſion of the title. For aſmuch as Magdeline was a woman, it behoued that ſhe ſhould be inferiour to her brother: therfore ſhe hath had but two bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, whereof the one is at Veſele nere Auſerre: and the other which is of greater renome, at S. Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mins in Prouince: There where the head is a part, with her <hi rend="roman">noli me tangere,</hi> whiche is a piece of waxe,
<pb facs="tcp:13073:51"/> which ſome doe thynke to be the marke that Ieſus Chriſt gaue her in deſpit becauſe he was ſory that ſhe woulde touch him. I make no mencion of the reliques that are diſparſed throughout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wel of her bones as of her here: he that wil haue the truth of this, he ſhould fyrſt of all enquire, to wit, if that Lazarus &amp; his two ſiſters, Martha, and Magdeline, were euer comme into Fraunce for to preache.</p>
            <p>For in readynge the auncient hiſtories, and in iudgynge of the whole matter wyth reaſon, one maye euidentlye ſee that it is the moſte folyſhe fable of the worlde: and the which hath as muche ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearaunce, as yf one dyd ſaye the cloudes are Calue ſkynnes: And neuertheles theſe are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſte cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayneſt Reliques that they haue.</p>
            <p>But yet yf it hadde bene ſo, it myght haue ſuffiſed to abuſe a bodye to Idolatrye, wythout ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of one Deuyll two or thre.
<pb facs="tcp:13073:52"/> Thei haue alſo canoniſed hin who peraſed the ſide of oure lorde Ieſus on the croſſe, and they haue called him ſainct Longes after haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſo baptiſed him they haue geuen him two bodyes, whereof the one is at Mantone, and the other at our la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the ile nere lions. Thei haue done the like of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſmen which came to worſhipe our lord Ieſus after his natiuitie. And firſt they haue determined of the number, ſayng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were but thre. The Goſpell maketh no mention how many they were: and certain aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient doctours haue ſaid, that they were fourtene: as he which wrote the imperfect commentarie vpon ſainct Matthewe, which ſome doth Intitle of Chryſoſtome moreouer in ſtead wher as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Goſpel nameth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> philoſophers, they haue made them. Kinges in haſte with ought Countrye and ſubiectes. Finally they haue baptiſede them naming the one Balthaſor, the other Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chior, and the other Gaſpar. Now
<pb facs="tcp:13073:52"/> although we did graunt all their fables, ſo friuolous and fonde as they are, it is certain that the wiſe men retournede into the eaſte cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trye. For the holye ſcripture ſo ſayeth, and one can not ſaye anye other wiſe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei died there.</p>
            <p>Who is it that hathe caried them awaye ſinſe? And who is it y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> knew them, for to marke them to the ende to make reliques in ſuch ſort of their bodyes? but I leaue it to Iudge forſomuch as it ſhoulde be but foliſhelye done of me for to redargue ſo euident mockeries. I only ſay, that they of Colongne, &amp; they of Milline, muſt fight which of the two ſhal haue them for they both pretende to haue them: The which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their proces ſhall be void, &amp; finiſhed, then will we auiſe, what ſhall be beaſt to be done. Amongeſt the auncient Mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters, ſainct denis is the moſt eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for ſome do take him for one of the Apoſtles diſciples, and the firſt Euangeliſte of fraunce. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb facs="tcp:13073:53"/> of this his dignity they haue of his reliques in diuerſſe places.</p>
            <p>Neuertheles, as thei ſay, the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy remaineth hole but onli in two places: at ſainct Denis in fraunce and at Regeſbourge in douchela<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the French men main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to haue him they of Regeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourge dyde make their proces at Rome. It is neare an hundrethe years a goe, &amp; the body was graun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted them by diffinitiall ſentence, the frenche Embaſſadour beyng preſent, whereof they haue a fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Bulle. Who ſo ſhall ſaye at ſainct denys nere Paris, that the body is not there, he ſhall be ſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, whoſoeuer contrariwiſe ſhall ſay that it is not at Regeſbourge, ſhall be helde for an Heritike for aſmuch as he ſhould be rebellious to the holy ſea Apoſtolike. So, it ſhall be moſt expedient, to make nor medell w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr quereles. Let them put out y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others eies if thei wil &amp; in ſo doing thei ſhal win nothing at all, except to diſcouer
<pb facs="tcp:13073:53"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their whole matter conſiſteth in liyng. They haue in ſuch ſort par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodi of S Steuen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is hole at Rome i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his church. His head in Arles, &amp; of his bones in more then<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. places. But for to ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts &amp; ſucceſſors of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> murdred the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, thei haue ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtones wherew<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was ſtoned: one might aſke where thei fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; out of whoſe ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds &amp; by what meanes thei haue gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I briefly anſwere y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is foliſh for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do wel know y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtones may be fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d euery where, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the cariage of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal coſt litle or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: thei do ſhew the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arles at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Auguſtins, at Viga<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gedoc. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil ſhut his eies &amp; his vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding wil beleue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei ar y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelf ſame ſtones wherw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſ. Ste<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen was ſtoned. He co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trariwiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil a litle co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider, wil mock at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; in dede y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> carmes of poiters haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d one w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in this .xiiii. yeres to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which thei haue aſſignd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office to deliuer wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of childbed: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bins
<pb facs="tcp:13073:54"/> from whom they had ſtolne one of ſainct Margarites ſides ſeruing to this vſe, haue made great bruite, criyng agaynſt their abuſe, but in the ende thei wan in keping good holde. I had almoſt determined to ſpeake nothing of the Innocents, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhuld haue gathe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red an army, thei would ſtyll alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge that this dothe not diſagre to the hiſtorie, becauſe that the num<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bre is not preſcribed, I leaue ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to ſpeake of the multitude. It ſuffiſeth that one note y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is of them in al the regions of the worlde. I now aſke how it is that they haue fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their ſepulchres ſo long time after, ſeing that they were not counted for ſaincts whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Herode put them to death: More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer when it was that they were caried away. Thei can anſwer me no other thing vnleſſe that it was fiue or ſixe hundred yeares after their death. I importe me to the moſte ſimpleſt idiots what a man may fynde, yf one ſhould beleue ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13073:54"/> abſurde things, put the caſe yet yf perchaunce there had certain bene founde, yet howe coulde it be that thei could cary diuers bodies into Fraunce, Dutchland, and Italy, for to diſtribut them in townes ſo farre of the one from the other? I leaue them this falſhead as alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicted. For aſmuch as ſainct Laurence is of the number of the auncient Martyrs, we wyll here geue him his place. I knowe not whether his body be in any more then one place, to wit, at Rome in the church named after his name. It is true that there is beſide a veſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſel of his fleſh broyled. Item two viols ful, the one of his blood, and the other of his greſe. Item there is in the church ſurnamed Paliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perne his arme and certain of his bones: &amp; at ſainct Silueſter other reliques. But if one would gather all the bones together which are onely in Fraunce: there would be ſufficient for to make whole large bodies. There foloweth after the
<pb facs="tcp:13073:55"/> Griderne I could well let it paſſe: but they haue other more notable thynges, of the whiche it is not lawfull for me to holde my peace. As coles whiche they do ſhewe at ſainct Euſtace. Item a napkyn, wherewith the angell wyped hys bodye. Seing they haue taken the leaſure to dreame ſuch inuencions to deceyue the world, let them al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that ſhall ſee this aduertiſment take the leaſure to thinke &amp; iudge of them, for to kepe them ſelues from being anye more diſceyued, and mocked. Out of the like forge is come his coope, which they do ſhow at Rome in ſainct Barbares church: becauſe thei haue hard ſay that S. Laure<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was a decon, thei thought it mete y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhuld haue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like garments as their decons ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue, diſguiſing their bodies in play<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing at the maſſe. But it was ano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther maner of office in thoſe daies in the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> church, then is now at this preſent in the Papiſtrie. Thei were thoſe that wer appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:13073:55"/> or choſen to diſtribute the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and not to playe Iugglers feats. So thei had no nede nether of ſirplices caps, tippets nor other foliſhe clothes for to diſguiſe them ſelues with. We wyll adde to S. Laurence S. Geruais and S. Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tais: whoſe ſepulchres wer found at Milan in S. Ambroſe time, as he himſelf teſtifieth. Likwiſe alſo S. Hierom, S. Auguſtine &amp; many others. And ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> towne of Millan maintaineth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe hath yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bodi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es beſides this not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding thei ar at Briſac in Duchla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; at Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in S. Peters church: beſides other infinite pieces which are diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſed in diuers churchs: ſo that it muſt nedes be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eueri one of them had .iiii. bodies at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, or els y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one do caſt al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bones y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ar ſhewed by falſe ſignes &amp; toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des. Forſomuch as thei haue geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> S. Sebaſtian y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of healing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> plague this hath bene y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath ben more required, &amp; that me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue ben more deſiroꝰ to haue him
<pb facs="tcp:13073:56"/> This credit and office hath made hym to be multiplied into foure whole bodies: whereof one is at Rome at S. Laurence church, the other at Soiſon, the third at Pil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lignie neare Nantes, the fourthe neare Narboune, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> place where he was borne. Beſides he hath two heades: the one at ſainct Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in Rome, &amp; the other at the Iacobines of Thoulouſe. It is true, they are but emptye ſculles, if one haue regarde to the Graye freres of Angiers who ſaye they haue the braine. Item the Iaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bines of Angiers haue an arme, and thei of ſainct Seruin of Thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>louſe another, another likewiſe at the caſe god of Auergne, and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at Mombriſon in the foreſt, beſides the ſmale litle pieces that are in many other churches. But when one ſhall haue well weyed the matter, then let one iudge where ſainct Sebaſtians body is. But they haue not bene ſatiſfied with all this, but they muſte alſo
<pb facs="tcp:13073:56"/> make reliques of the arrowes wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with he was ſhotten: whereof they ſhew one at Lambeſt in prouince an other at Poiters at the Auguſtins, and the others here &amp; there. By this men mai euidently ſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei thought neuer to make account of their decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. A like reaſon hath auailed to S. Anthony for the multipliyng of his reliques: for becauſe that he is a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick and dangerous ſainct, as thei fain him, who doth burne whom ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he is angrie with: by this opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion he makes him ſelf to be feared and douted. The fear hath enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred deuotion, the which hath ſharpened the appetite, for to make his body to be more deſired becauſe of the profit. Wherfore the towne of Arles hath had great &amp; long combat againſt the Antoniens of Venis: but the iſſue &amp; ende therof was no other then hath bene accuſtomed to be in ſuch a mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. To wit, al remaineth ſtil in con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſion. For if a man would haue tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out the truth, neither of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſhoulde haue any good cauſe.
<pb facs="tcp:13073:57"/> Wyth theſe two bodyes there is a kne at the Auguſtines of Albi: there is at Burge at Maſcon, at Dion, at Chalous, at Ourour, at Beſanſon, reliques of diuers membres: beſides that which the abuſers cary fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey to countrey, which is no ſmall quantitie. Behold what a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it is to haue an ill name: for w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> out thys, the good S. ſhuld haue remayned in his graue, or in ſome certain corner without any ſpeaking of him at all. I had forgotten S. Petronel y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghter of ſainct Peter, who hath her body whole at Rome in her fathers church: Item more reliques beſides at ſainct Barbares. But yet neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles ſhe wanteth not therefore to haue another bodye at Maus, in the Iacobines couent: the which is ther had in greate ſolemnitie, becauſe it doth heale agues. For ſo muche as there hath bene diuers ſayncts na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Suſan, I cannot wel tel if their intentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue bene to attribute two bodies to one. But yet is it that S. Suſan hath one bodye at Rome in
<pb facs="tcp:13073:57"/> the church called after her name, and another at Thoulouſe. Sainct He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lene hath not bene ſo happy: for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her body that is at Veniſe, ſhe hath wonne no more, then one head only, the which is at ſainct Gerion of Colongne. Sainct Vrſulye hath ſurmonted her herein: for firſt her bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dye is at ſainct Iohn of Angell: ſhe hath moreouer a heade at Cologne, one portion at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iacobins of Maus, another at the Iacobines of Tours the other at Bergerate. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the companye, which men doe call the eleuen thouſande virgins, they maye well haue of them euery where. And in dede, they haue bene much boldned herby, for to lye more largely and liberaly. For beſides an an hundred cartesful of bones, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are at Cologne, ther is ſcarſly no towne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al Europa, which ar not furniſhed therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, either i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one church or many. If I ſhuld begin to e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>treat of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſort of ſaincts, I ſhuld enter into a fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reſt, wheras I ſhuld neuer find way to go out: wherefore I wyll alledge
<pb facs="tcp:13073:58"/> certain examples in bypaſſing wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by one may eaſly iudge of al the reſt. At Poiters there are two churches which ar at varience for S. Hilaries bodye: to wit, the Chanons of hys church, and the monkes of Selle. The debate or proces remaineth, vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>till viſitation be made. In the mean time the Idolaters ſhalbe conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to worſhippe two bodyes of one man: the faithfull ſhall leaue the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy at reſt, where as it is, not caring for it. As concerning ſainct Honorat his body is at Arles, and alſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe at the yle of Lyrens, near An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibon. Sainct Giles hath one of hys bodies at Thoulouſe, &amp; another at a towne of Langedoc, which beareth his name. Sainct William is in an abbey of Langedoc, named S. Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam of the wildernes, and alſo in a towne of Auſſoy, named Ecrichen, with the head apart: albeit y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hath another head in the ſuburbe of Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren in Iulle, in the abbey of the Gui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liernites. What ſhal I ſai of S. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phorin or Simphorien, who is in ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13073:58"/> many places, both i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whole bodies &amp; in bones? likwiſe of ſ. Woulfe, who is at Aſſerre at Senes, at Lion, and alſo ſome did make men beleue that he was at Geneue. Aſmuch of ſainct Ferreoll, who is altogether whole at Vze in Langedoc, and at Brinde in Auergne. At the leaſte it is nede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful they ſhoulde conſult together for ſome good remedye, that their lyes maye not be ſo much diſcouered: as the Chanons of Trier haue done w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> them of Lieg, touchyng the head of ſainct Lambert: for they haue geuen a certaine ſumme of money, for the intereſt of the offerings, to the ende they ſhould not publikly ſhew them for feare leaſt men ſhould be aſtoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed to ſee them in two townes ſo neare together. But it is as I haue ſaid in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning thei haue neuer thoght or loked for to haue any that ſhould controle them, who durſte be ſo bolde as to open his mouth for to declare and ſhew their impudencie. One might aſke how theſe relique Iugglers, ſeyng that they haue ſo
<pb facs="tcp:13073:59"/> vainlye &amp; curiouſly imagined al that hath come in their braines, and in blowyng haue forged what ſoeuer hath pleaſed them) haue left behind them and forgotten y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> notable thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the olde teſtament. To this I know not what to anſwer, but that thei haue deſpiſed them, becauſe that thei hoped for no great profit of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But yet they haue not all together forgotten them: for at Rome at S. Maries aboue Minerue, they ſaye they haue the bones of Abraham, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſac, and Iacob. At ſainct Iohn of La<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trans thei boſte to haue the arcke of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenant, with Aarons rodde: and yet neuertheleſſe, this rod is alſo at the holy chappell of Paris, and they of Sayncte Sauiours in Spayne haue a certaine piece.</p>
            <p>Moreouer beſides this thei of Bur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deaur affirme that the rod of ſainct Mertial, which is ſhewed ther in S. Seuerins church, is the ſelf ſame of Aaron. It ſemeth that thei woulde haue made a new miracle, to enuye god w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>: for as this rod was turned in
<pb facs="tcp:13073:59"/> to a ſerpent by his vertue, euen ſo nowe thei haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted it into thre rods. It may wel be y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei haue ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny other monakles of the olde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: but this wherof we haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuffiſeth to declare y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue as largely delt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this parte as w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſt. I now pray thee reader to be mindfull of that which I haue ſaide in the beginninge. That is, that I haue not had commiſſioners for to viſit the reliques of al the countreys whiche I haue here before mencio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, that whiche I haue ſaid muſt not be taken or counted, as a ful and perfect regeſter or inuento<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, of all that may be founde.</p>
            <p>For I haue named but onelye a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute halfe a douſen Townes of Doutchelande. I haue named but thre of Spaine, as farre as I know. Of Italye, aboute the numbre of fyftene. Of Fraunce from thyrtye to fourtye: And yet of thoſe haue I not ſpoken, all that is to be ſayde in that behalfe. Let euerye one then
<pb facs="tcp:13073:60"/> coniecture in himſelf what a heape &amp; nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre it ſhuld be if one ſhuld orderly place y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> multitude of reliques y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are through out al chriſtendom. I mean only the countreys that we know, &amp; where as we vſe to trauail. For the principal is to note that all the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques that they do ſhew in theſe coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>treys of Ieſus Chriſt, and of the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes, men ſhal find them aſwel in Grecia and in Aſia, and in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gions where as there are Chriſtian churches. But I nowe aſke, that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the orientall chriſtian churches ſay that all that we thinke we haue here with vs, is with them, what re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolution or aſſurance one may haue thereof? If one ſhuld contrary them alledging that ſuch a ſainctes bodie was brought away by marchantes, another by monks, another by a bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop: one part of the crown of thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes was ſent to a king of Fraunce, by the emperour of Conſtantinoble the other part conquered by war, &amp; ſo of al the other pieces: thei would nodde and lifte their heades in moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kage.
<pb facs="tcp:13073:60"/> Howe ſhall one auoyde theſe quarelles? For in a doutfull matter it is requiſite to Iudge by coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res. Nowe in ſo doyng they ſhoulde alwayes wynne the vpper hand: for that which thei haue to ſai for theyr part, is more lyke to be trewe, then all that one can pretende of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie on this ſide. It is a troubleſome and angry matter to intermedel for them that woulde defende reliques. For to make an ende, I pray and ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>hort all readers in the name of God to employ them ſelues to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trueth, whileſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is ſo manifeſt and openly ſhewed them, &amp; acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge that this is done by a ſinguler prouidence of God, that they who woulde haue in ſuche ſorte decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the poore worlde, haue bene ſo blynde that they haue not conſidred or thoughte howe they myght haue had better hid and couered their lies but as the Madianites who hauyng their eyes pulled out, were at ſtrife and varience the one agaynſt the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So we ſee that they make war
<pb facs="tcp:13073:61"/> againſt them ſelues, and mutuallye belye the one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> others. Whoſoeuer wil not harden th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r heartes, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne againſt al reaſon, and truth. Albeit that he be not fullye inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted or perſuaded in him ſelf, that it is execrable Idolatrie, to worſhippe any kinde of relique what ſo euer it be: yet neuertheleſſe he ſeing ſo eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent falſheade, ſhall neuer haue the heart ſo much as to kiſſe any one of them: and what deuotion ſo euer he hath had to them before, it ſhall be fullye and altogether extinguiſhed. The principall ſhould be as I haue ſayd in the beginning to aboliſhe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt vs chriſtians this heathen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuperſtition, of canoniſing the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, aſwell of Ieſus Chriſte as of his ſaincts, for to make idols. This kind of doinge is a filthy polution y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which ought in no wiſe to be ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the church. We haue already ſhowed by what reaſons, and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the ſcripture it ſhuld be ſo. If any be not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent or ſatiſfied ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>with, let him conſider the vſe of the
<pb facs="tcp:13073:61"/> auncient fathers, to the end to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme him ſelf after their examples. There hath bene many holy patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arches, many prophetes, many god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kings, &amp; other faithfull in the old teſtament: God had ordeyned more ceremonies in that tyme, then we ought to haue in our tyme: Yea, it was requiſite that the buriyng pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhoulde be more gorgeouſlye and fairer made, then now, for to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent by figure and ſhadowe the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reſurrection, for ſo much as it was not ſo clerely reueiled by word as we haue it: doe we read that they haue plucked the bodies of ſainctes out of their ſepulchres for to make puppies of them? Abraham the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of al the faithfull, was he euer taken vp? Sara alſo Princeſſe in the Churche of GOD, hath ſhe bene taken oute of her graue? Haue not they lefte them at reſt with all the other ſaynctes?</p>
            <p>Moreouer Moyſes bodye, was not it hydde by the wyll of God, ſo that men could neuer finde it?</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:13073:62"/>
            <p>Hath not the deuil foughten againſt the angels as ſainct Iude ſaieth? Wherefore is it that the lorde hath hyd it from mans ſight, and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil would there again place it? It is as euery one doth confeſſe that God would take from his people of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell the occaſion of Idolatrie: The de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uil on the contrary part would eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhe it. But ſome will ſay the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſrael were inclined to ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition. I aſke what we are: is there not without compariſon more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie amongeſt the chriſtians con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning this matter, then euer was amongeſt the Iewes? Let vs conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what was done in the auncient churche: I graunt you the faithfull, haue alwayes taken paines to with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>draw the bodies of Martyrs, for that they ſhould not be eaten of dogges, or beaſts, or byrdes, &amp; haue honeſtly buried them: as we reade both of S. Iohn Baptiſt and of ſainct Steuen. But this was done for to bury them in the earth, for to leaue them there vntyll the daye of the reſurrection:
<pb facs="tcp:13073:62"/> and not for to place them in mans ſyght, for men to knele before them. This wycked pompe of canoniſyng them was neuer broughte into the church, vntyll ſuch tyme as all was peruerted, and as it were propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: partly by the beaſtlineſſe of the prieſtes and paſtors, partly by their couetouſnes, partly alſo becauſe thei could not reſiſt the cuſtome, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was receyued: And partly in that the people did ſeeke to be abuſed in ſetting their mindes rather on chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſhe playes, then on the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippynge of God. Therefore, that which hath bene ill begon and eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed againſt all reaſon, oughte to be clean aboliſhed, who ſo wil right<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly correcte the abuſe. But if one can not come at the firſt to thys vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, at the leſt let him come by litle and litle: and let him open his eyes for to diſcerne what the reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques are that they do ſhewe. Nowe this is not harde to be ſene, to them that wyll vnderſtand. For amonge ſo manye euident lyes, as I haue
<pb facs="tcp:13073:63"/> mencioned where ſhall a man choſe one true relique, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which he may be certainly aſſured? Moreouer, this is in a maner nothing which I haue touched, in value of that which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maineth. Yea in the meane time as this boke was a printing, one dyd ſhew me of the third foreſkyn of our lord Ieſus, which is ſhewed at Hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſhem, whereof I had made no mencion. There is an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſuch like. Finally the viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them would diſcloſe and vnco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer yet an hundred times more then al that one could ſay or ſpeake ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. So then let euery one particuler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take hede that he ſuffer not hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as a beaſt to be drawen or led af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter his own braine, not perceyuing neither way nor meanes for to haue any grounde. I remembre that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch I haue ſene done to the idols of our countrey, being at that time a li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tle child. When ſainct Steuens day drew nere, one did aſwell trym the hattes and images of the tirauntes that ſtoned him (for ſo thei are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:13073:63"/> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> language) as his image The poore ſimple women, ſeing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyrantes ſo decked and ſet in order, toke them for Sainct Steuens fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, and ſo euery one of them had their candell. And moreouer this was done to the diuell Sainct Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bell. So is it of the relique: for all is ſo mingled and confuſed, that one can not worſhyp the bone of a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, but he ſhall be in danger to wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip the bones of ſome certaine Mur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>therer or thefe, or els of an aſſe, or of a dog, or of a horſſe, neither can one worſhyp our ladyes ringes, or her comme, or girdell, but one ſhall be in danger of worſhipping the ringes of ſome certaine hoore. Wherefore, take hede of the danger who ſo will for none from henſe forth can pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende any excuſe of ignoraunce.</p>
            <trailer>
               <hi rend="roman">FINIS.</hi>
            </trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
